<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-14T10:34:26+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Samuel Hsiang</title><subtitle>My little corner of the web.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Aeneid, Book I</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2020/06/13/aeneid/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Aeneid, Book I" /><published>2020-06-14T07:50:00+04:00</published><updated>2020-06-14T07:50:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2020/06/13/aeneid</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2020/06/13/aeneid/">&lt;p&gt;Translated by A. S. Kline. Formatting in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Bootstrap CSS --&gt;
&lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; href=&quot;https://stackpath.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/4.5.0/css/bootstrap.min.css&quot; integrity=&quot;sha384-9aIt2nRpC12Uk9gS9baDl411NQApFmC26EwAOH8WgZl5MYYxFfc+NcPb1dKGj7Sk&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot; /&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.jquery.com/jquery-3.5.1.slim.min.js&quot; integrity=&quot;sha384-DfXdz2htPH0lsSSs5nCTpuj/zy4C+OGpamoFVy38MVBnE+IbbVYUew+OrCXaRkfj&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/popper.js@1.16.0/dist/umd/popper.min.js&quot; integrity=&quot;sha384-Q6E9RHvbIyZFJoft+2mJbHaEWldlvI9IOYy5n3zV9zzTtmI3UksdQRVvoxMfooAo&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://stackpath.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/4.5.0/js/bootstrap.min.js&quot; integrity=&quot;sha384-OgVRvuATP1z7JjHLkuOU7Xw704+h835Lr+6QL9UvYjZE3Ipu6Tp75j7Bh/kR0JKI&quot; crossorigin=&quot;anonymous&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; style=&quot;font-size:8px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; Arma virumque canō, Trōiae quī prīmus ab ōrīs&lt;br /&gt; Ītaliam,
fātō profugus, Lāvīniaque vēnit&lt;br /&gt; lītora, multum ille et terrīs
iactātus et altō&lt;br /&gt; vī superum saevae memorem Iūnōnis ob īram;&lt;br /&gt;                multa quoque et bellō passūs, dum conderet urbem,&lt;br /&gt; inferretque
deōs Latiō, genus unde Latīnum,&lt;br /&gt; Albānīque patrēs, atque altae
moenia Rōmae.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; I sing of arms and the man, he who, exiled by fate,
&lt;br /&gt; first came from the coast of Troy to Italy, and to
&lt;br /&gt; Lavinian shores – hurled about endlessly by land and sea,
&lt;br /&gt; by the will of the gods, by cruel Juno’s remorseless anger,
&lt;br /&gt; long suffering also in war, until he founded a city
&lt;br /&gt; and brought his gods to Latium: from that the Latin people
&lt;br /&gt; came, the lords of Alba Longa, the walls of noble Rome.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; Mūsa, mihī causās memorā, quō nūmine laesō,&lt;br /&gt; quidve dolēns,
rēgīna deum tot volvere cāsūs&lt;br /&gt; īnsīgnem pietāte virum, tot adīre
labōrēs
&lt;br /&gt; impulerit. Tantaene animīs caelestibus īrae?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; Muse, tell me the cause: how was she offended in her divinity,
&lt;br /&gt; how was she grieved, the Queen of Heaven, to drive a man,
&lt;br /&gt; noted for virtue, to endure such dangers, to face so many
&lt;br /&gt; trials? Can there be such anger in the minds of the gods?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; Urbs antīqua fuit, Tyriī tenuēre colōnī,&lt;br /&gt; Karthāgō, Ītaliam
contrā Tiberīnaque longē&lt;br /&gt; ōstia, dīves opum studiīsque asperrima
bellī,
&lt;br /&gt; quam Iūnō fertur terrīs magis omnibus ūnam&lt;br /&gt; posthabitā
coluisse Samō; hīc illius arma,&lt;br /&gt; hīc currus fuit; hōc rēgnum
dea gentibus esse,&lt;br /&gt; sī quā Fāta sinant, iam tum tenditque fovetque.
&lt;br /&gt; Prōgeniem sed enim Trōiānō ā sanguine dūcī&lt;br /&gt; audierat, Tyriās
olim quae verteret arcēs;&lt;br /&gt; hinc populum lātē regem bellōque
superbum
&lt;br /&gt; ventūrum excidiō Libyae: sīc volvere Parcās.&lt;br /&gt; Id metuēns,
veterisque memor Sāturnia bellī,&lt;br /&gt; prīma quod ad Trōiam prō cārīs
gesserat Argīs&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt; necdum etiam causae īrārum saevīque dolōrēs
&lt;br /&gt; exciderant animō: manet altā mente repostum&lt;br /&gt; iūdicium Paridis
sprētaeque iniūria fōrmae,&lt;br /&gt; et genus invīsum, et raptī Ganymēdis
honōrēs.
&lt;br /&gt; Hīs accēnsa super, iactātōs aequore tōtō&lt;br /&gt; Trōas, rēliquiās
Danaum atque immītis Achillī,&lt;br /&gt; arcēbat longē Latiō, multōsque
per annōs&lt;br /&gt; errābant, āctī Fātīs, maria omnia circum.
&lt;br /&gt; Tantae mōlis erat Rōmānam condere gentem!
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There was an ancient city, Carthage (held by colonists from Tyre),
&lt;br /&gt;opposite Italy, and the far-off mouths of the Tiber,
&lt;br /&gt;rich in wealth, and very savage in pursuit of war.
&lt;br /&gt;They say Juno loved this one land above all others,
&lt;br /&gt;even neglecting Samos: here were her weapons
&lt;br /&gt;and her chariot, even then the goddess worked at,
&lt;br /&gt;and cherished, the idea that it should have supremacy
&lt;br /&gt;over the nations, if only the fates allowed.
&lt;br /&gt;Yet she’d heard of offspring, derived from Trojan blood,
&lt;br /&gt;that would one day overthrow the Tyrian stronghold:
&lt;br /&gt;that from them a people would come, wide-ruling,
&lt;br /&gt;and proud in war, to Libya’s ruin: so the Fates ordained.
&lt;br /&gt;Fearing this, and remembering the ancient war
&lt;br /&gt;she had fought before, at Troy, for her dear Argos,
&lt;br /&gt;(and the cause of her anger and bitter sorrows
&lt;br /&gt;had not yet passed from her mind: the distant judgement
&lt;br /&gt;of Paris stayed deep in her heart, the injury to her scorned
beauty,
&lt;br /&gt;her hatred of the race, and abducted Ganymede’s honours)
&lt;br /&gt;the daughter of Saturn, incited further by this,
&lt;br /&gt;hurled the Trojans, the Greeks and pitiless Achilles had left,
&lt;br /&gt;round the whole ocean, keeping them far from Latium:
&lt;br /&gt;they wandered for many years, driven by fate over all the seas.
&lt;br /&gt;Such an effort it was to found the Roman people.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Vix e conspectu Siculae telluris in altum&lt;br /&gt; vela dabant laeti,
et spumas salis aere ruebant,&lt;br /&gt; cum Iuno, aeternum servans sub
pectore volnus,&lt;br /&gt; haec secum: 'Mene incepto desistere victam,&lt;br /&gt;                nec posse Italia Teucrorum avertere regem?&lt;br /&gt; Quippe vetor fatis.
Pallasne exurere classem&lt;br /&gt; Argivom atque ipsos potuit submergere
ponto,
&lt;br /&gt; unius ob noxam et furias Aiacis Oilei?&lt;br /&gt; Ipsa, Iovis rapidum
iaculata e nubibus ignem,&lt;br /&gt; disiecitque rates evertitque aequora
ventis,
&lt;br /&gt; illum expirantem transfixo pectore flammas&lt;br /&gt; turbine corripuit
scopuloque infixit acuto.&lt;br /&gt; Ast ego, quae divom incedo regina,
Iovisque
&lt;br /&gt; et soror et coniunx, una cum gente tot annos&lt;br /&gt; bella gero!
Et quisquam numen Iunonis adoret&lt;br /&gt; praeterea, aut supplex aris
imponet honorem?'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;They were hardly out of sight of Sicily’s isle, in deeper water,
&lt;br /&gt;joyfully spreading sail, bronze keel ploughing the brine,
&lt;br /&gt;when Juno, nursing the eternal wound in her breast,
&lt;br /&gt;spoke to herself: ‘Am I to abandon my purpose, conquered,
&lt;br /&gt;unable to turn the Teucrian king away from Italy!
&lt;br /&gt;Why, the fates forbid it. Wasn’t Pallas able to burn
&lt;br /&gt;the Argive fleet, to sink it in the sea, because of the guilt
&lt;br /&gt;and madness of one single man, Ajax, son of Oileus?
&lt;br /&gt;She herself hurled Jupiter’s swift fire from the clouds,
&lt;br /&gt;scattered the ships, and made the sea boil with storms:
&lt;br /&gt;She caught him up in a water-spout, as he breathed flame
&lt;br /&gt;from his pierced chest, and pinned him to a sharp rock:
&lt;br /&gt;yet I, who walk about as queen of the gods, wife
&lt;br /&gt;and sister of Jove, wage war on a whole race, for so many years.
&lt;br /&gt;Indeed, will anyone worship Juno’s power from now on,
&lt;br /&gt;or place offerings, humbly, on her altars?’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; Talia flammato secum dea corde volutans&lt;br /&gt; nimborum in patriam,
loca feta furentibus austris,&lt;br /&gt; Aeoliam venit. Hic vasto rex
Aeolus antro&lt;br /&gt; luctantes ventos tempestatesque sonoras&lt;br /&gt; imperio
premit ac vinclis et carcere frenat.&lt;br /&gt; Illi indignantes magno
cum murmure montis&lt;br /&gt; circum claustra fremunt; celsa sedet Aeolus
arce
&lt;br /&gt; sceptra tenens, mollitque animos et temperat iras.&lt;br /&gt; Ni
faciat, maria ac terras caelumque profundum&lt;br /&gt; quippe ferant rapidi
secum verrantque per auras.&lt;br /&gt; Sed pater omnipotens speluncis
abdidit atris,&lt;br /&gt; hoc metuens, molemque et montis insuper altos&lt;br /&gt;                imposuit, regemque dedit, qui foedere certo&lt;br /&gt; et premere et laxas
sciret dare iussus habenas.&lt;br /&gt; Ad quem tum Iuno supplex his vocibus
usa est:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt; So debating with herself, her heart inflamed, the goddess
&lt;br /&gt;came to Aeolia, to the country of storms, the place
&lt;br /&gt;of wild gales. Here in his vast cave, King Aeolus,
&lt;br /&gt;keeps the writhing winds, and the roaring tempests,
&lt;br /&gt;under control, curbs them with chains and imprisonment.
&lt;br /&gt;They moan angrily at the doors, with a mountain’s vast murmurs:
&lt;br /&gt;Aeolus sits, holding his sceptre, in his high stronghold,
&lt;br /&gt;softening their passions, tempering their rage: if not,
&lt;br /&gt;they’d surely carry off seas and lands and the highest heavens,
&lt;br /&gt;with them, in rapid flight, and sweep them through the air.
&lt;br /&gt;But the all-powerful Father, fearing this, hid them
&lt;br /&gt;in dark caves, and piled a high mountain mass over them
&lt;br /&gt;and gave them a king, who by fixed agreement, would know
&lt;br /&gt;how to give the order to tighten or slacken the reins.
&lt;br /&gt;Juno now offered these words to him, humbly:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 'Aeole, namque tibi divom pater atque hominum rex&lt;br /&gt; et mulcere
dedit fluctus et tollere vento,&lt;br /&gt; gens inimica mihi Tyrrhenum
navigat aequor,
&lt;br /&gt; Ilium in Italiam portans victosque Penates:
&lt;br /&gt; incute vim ventis submersasque obrue puppes,&lt;br /&gt; aut age diversos
et disiice corpora ponto.&lt;br /&gt; Sunt mihi bis septem praestanti corpore
nymphae,
&lt;br /&gt; quarum quae forma pulcherrima Deiopea,&lt;br /&gt; conubio iungam
stabili propriamque dicabo,&lt;br /&gt; omnis ut tecum meritis pro talibus
annos
&lt;br /&gt; exigat, et pulchra faciat te prole parentem.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt; ‘Aeolus, since the Father of gods, and king of men,
&lt;br /&gt;gave you the power to quell, and raise, the waves with the
winds,
&lt;br /&gt;there is a people I hate sailing the Tyrrhenian Sea,
&lt;br /&gt;bringing Troy’s conquered gods to Italy:
&lt;br /&gt;Add power to the winds, and sink their wrecked boats,
&lt;br /&gt;or drive them apart, and scatter their bodies over the sea.
&lt;br /&gt;I have fourteen Nymphs of outstanding beauty:
&lt;br /&gt;of whom I’ll name Deiopea, the loveliest in looks,
&lt;br /&gt;joined in eternal marriage, and yours for ever, so that,
&lt;br /&gt;for such service to me as yours, she’ll spend all her years
&lt;br /&gt;with you, and make you the father of lovely children.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Aeolus haec contra: 'Tuus, O regina, quid optes&lt;br /&gt; explorare labor;
mihi iussa capessere fas est.&lt;br /&gt; Tu mihi, quodcumque hoc regni,
tu sceptra Iovemque&lt;br /&gt; concilias, tu das epulis accumbere divom,
&lt;br /&gt; nimborumque facis tempestatumque potentem.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Aeolus replied: ‘Your task, O queen, is to decide
&lt;br /&gt;what you wish: my duty is to fulfil your orders.
&lt;br /&gt;You brought about all this kingdom of mine, the sceptre,
&lt;br /&gt;Jove’s favour, you gave me a seat at the feasts of the gods,
&lt;br /&gt;and you made me lord of the storms and the tempests.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Haec ubi dicta, cavum conversa cuspide montem&lt;br /&gt; impulit in latus:
ac venti, velut agmine facto,&lt;br /&gt; qua data porta, ruunt et terras
turbine perflant.&lt;br /&gt; Incubuere mari, totumque a sedibus imis
&lt;br /&gt; una Eurusque Notusque ruunt creberque procellis&lt;br /&gt; Africus,
et vastos volvunt ad litora fluctus.&lt;br /&gt; Insequitur clamorque virum
stridorque rudentum.&lt;br /&gt; Eripiunt subito nubes caelumque diemque&lt;br /&gt;                Teucrorum ex oculis; ponto nox incubat atra.&lt;br /&gt; Intonuere poli,
et crebris micat ignibus aether,&lt;br /&gt; praesentemque viris intentant
omnia mortem.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;When he had spoken, he reversed his trident and struck
&lt;br /&gt;the hollow mountain on the side: and the winds, formed ranks,
&lt;br /&gt;rushed out by the door he’d made, and whirled across the earth.
&lt;br /&gt;They settle on the sea, East and West wind,
&lt;br /&gt;and the wind from Africa, together, thick with storms,
&lt;br /&gt;stir it all from its furthest deeps, and roll vast waves to
shore:
&lt;br /&gt;follows a cry of men and a creaking of cables.
&lt;br /&gt;Suddenly clouds take sky and day away
&lt;br /&gt;from the Trojan’s eyes: dark night rests on the sea.
&lt;br /&gt;It thunders from the pole, and the aether flashes thick fire,
&lt;br /&gt;and all things threaten immediate death to men.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Extemplo Aeneae solvuntur frigore membra:&lt;br /&gt; ingemit, et duplicis
tendens ad sidera palmas&lt;br /&gt; talia voce refert: 'O terque quaterque
beati,
&lt;br /&gt; quis ante ora patrum Troiae sub moenibus altis
&lt;br /&gt; contigit oppetere! O Danaum fortissime gentis&lt;br /&gt; Tydide!
Mene Iliacis occumbere campis&lt;br /&gt; non potuisse, tuaque animam hanc
effundere dextra,&lt;br /&gt; saevus ubi Aeacidae telo iacet Hector, ubi
ingens
&lt;br /&gt; Sarpedon, ubi tot Simois correpta sub undis&lt;br /&gt; scuta virum
galeasque et fortia corpora volvit?'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Instantly Aeneas groans, his limbs slack with cold:
&lt;br /&gt;stretching his two hands towards the heavens,
&lt;br /&gt;he cries out in this voice: ‘Oh, three, four times fortunate
&lt;br /&gt;were those who chanced to die in front of their father’s eyes
&lt;br /&gt;under Troy’s high walls! O Diomede, son of Tydeus
&lt;br /&gt;bravest of Greeks! Why could I not have fallen, at your hand,
&lt;br /&gt;in the fields of Ilium, and poured out my spirit,
&lt;br /&gt;where fierce Hector lies, beneath Achilles’s spear,
&lt;br /&gt;and mighty Sarpedon: where Simois rolls, and sweeps away
&lt;br /&gt;so many shields, helmets, brave bodies, of men, in its waves!’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; Talia iactanti stridens Aquilone procella&lt;br /&gt; velum adversa
ferit, fluctusque ad sidera tollit.&lt;br /&gt; Franguntur remi; tum prora
avertit, et undis&lt;br /&gt; dat latus; insequitur cumulo praeruptus aquae
mons.
&lt;br /&gt; Hi summo in fluctu pendent; his unda dehiscens&lt;br /&gt; terram
inter fluctus aperit; furit aestus harenis.&lt;br /&gt; Tris Notus abreptas
in saxa latentia torquet&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt; saxa vocant Itali mediis quae
in fluctibus aras&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt; dorsum immane mari summo; tris Eurus
ab alto&lt;br /&gt; in brevia et Syrtis urget, miserabile visu,&lt;br /&gt; inliditque
vadis atque aggere cingit harenae.&lt;br /&gt; Unam, quae Lycios fidumque
vehebat Oronten,&lt;br /&gt; ipsius ante oculos ingens a vertice pontus&lt;br /&gt;                in puppim ferit: excutitur pronusque magister&lt;br /&gt; volvitur in caput;
ast illam ter fluctus ibidem&lt;br /&gt; torquet agens circum, et rapidus
vorat aequore vortex.&lt;br /&gt; Adparent rari nantes in gurgite vasto,&lt;br /&gt;                arma virum, tabulaeque, et Troia gaza per undas.&lt;br /&gt; Iam validam
Ilionei navem, iam fortis Achati,&lt;br /&gt; et qua vectus Abas, et qua
grandaevus Aletes,&lt;br /&gt; vicit hiems; laxis laterum compagibus omnes&lt;br /&gt;                accipiunt inimicum imbrem, rimisque fatiscunt.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Hurling these words out, a howling blast from the north,
&lt;br /&gt;strikes square on the sail, and lifts the seas to heaven:
&lt;br /&gt;the oars break: then the prow swings round and offers
&lt;br /&gt;the beam to the waves: a steep mountain of water follows in
a mass.
&lt;br /&gt;Some ships hang on the breaker’s crest: to others the yawning
deep
&lt;br /&gt;shows land between the waves: the surge rages with sand.
&lt;br /&gt;The south wind catches three, and whirls them onto hidden rocks
&lt;br /&gt;(rocks the Italians call the Altars, in mid-ocean,
&lt;br /&gt;a vast reef on the surface of the sea) three the east wind
drives
&lt;br /&gt;from the deep, to the shallows and quick-sands (a pitiful sight),
&lt;br /&gt;dashes them against the bottom, covers them with a gravel mound.
&lt;br /&gt;A huge wave, toppling, strikes one astern, in front of his
very eyes,
&lt;br /&gt;one carrying faithful Orontes and the Lycians.
&lt;br /&gt;The steersman’s thrown out and hurled headlong, face down:
&lt;br /&gt;but the sea turns the ship three times, driving her round,
&lt;br /&gt;in place, and the swift vortex swallows her in the deep.
&lt;br /&gt;Swimmers appear here and there in the vast waste,
&lt;br /&gt;men’s weapons, planking, Trojan treasure in the waves.
&lt;br /&gt;Now the storm conquers Iloneus’s tough ship, now Achates,
&lt;br /&gt;now that in which Abas sailed, and old Aletes’s:
&lt;br /&gt;their timbers sprung in their sides, all the ships
&lt;br /&gt;let in the hostile tide, and split open at the seams.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Interea magno misceri murmure pontum,&lt;br /&gt; emissamque hiemem sensit
Neptunus, et imis&lt;br /&gt; stagna refusa vadis, graviter commotus; et
alto
&lt;br /&gt; prospiciens, summa placidum caput extulit unda.&lt;br /&gt; Disiectam
Aeneae, toto videt aequore classem,&lt;br /&gt; fluctibus oppressos Troas
caelique ruina,&lt;br /&gt; nec latuere doli fratrem Iunonis et irae.&lt;br /&gt;                Eurum ad se Zephyrumque vocat, dehinc talia fatur:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Neptune, meanwhile, greatly troubled, saw that the sea
&lt;br /&gt;was churned with vast murmur, and the storm was loose
&lt;br /&gt;and the still waters welled from their deepest levels:
&lt;br /&gt;he raised his calm face from the waves, gazing over the deep.
&lt;br /&gt;He sees Aeneas’s fleet scattered all over the ocean,
&lt;br /&gt;the Trojans crushed by the breakers, and the plummeting sky.
&lt;br /&gt;And Juno’s anger, and her stratagems, do not escape her brother.
&lt;br /&gt;He calls the East and West winds to him, and then says:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;'Tantane vos generis tenuit fiducia vestri?&lt;br /&gt; Iam caelum terramque
meo sine numine, venti,&lt;br /&gt; miscere, et tantas audetis tollere
moles?
&lt;br /&gt; Quos ego&amp;#151;sed motos praestat componere fluctus.&lt;br /&gt; Post
mihi non simili poena commissa luetis.&lt;br /&gt; Maturate fugam, regique
haec dicite vestro:&lt;br /&gt; non illi imperium pelagi saevumque tridentem,
&lt;br /&gt; sed mihi sorte datum. Tenet ille immania saxa,&lt;br /&gt; vestras,
Eure, domos; illa se iactet in aula&lt;br /&gt; Aeolus, et clauso ventorum
carcere regnet.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;‘Does confidence in your birth fill you so? Winds, do you dare,
&lt;br /&gt;without my intent, to mix earth with sky, and cause such trouble,
&lt;br /&gt;now? You whom I – ! But it’s better to calm the running waves:
&lt;br /&gt;you’ll answer to me later for this misfortune, with a different
punishment.
&lt;br /&gt;Hurry, fly now, and say this to your king:
&lt;br /&gt;control of the ocean, and the fierce trident, were given to
me,
&lt;br /&gt;by lot, and not to him. He owns the wild rocks, home to you,
&lt;br /&gt;and yours, East Wind: let Aeolus officiate in his palace,
&lt;br /&gt;and be king in the closed prison of the winds.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Sic ait, et dicto citius tumida aequora placat,&lt;br /&gt; collectasque
fugat nubes, solemque reducit.&lt;br /&gt; Cymothoe simul et Triton adnixus
acuto
&lt;br /&gt; detrudunt navis scopulo; levat ipse tridenti;&lt;br /&gt; et vastas
aperit syrtis, et temperat aequor,&lt;br /&gt; atque rotis summas levibus
perlabitur undas.&lt;br /&gt; Ac veluti magno in populo cum saepe coorta
est
&lt;br /&gt; seditio, saevitque animis ignobile volgus,&lt;br /&gt; iamque faces
et saxa volant&amp;#151;furor arma ministrat;&lt;br /&gt; tum, pietate gravem
ac meritis si forte virum quem&lt;br /&gt; conspexere, silent, arrectisque
auribus adstant;&lt;br /&gt; ille regit dictis animos, et pectora mulcet,&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt;                sic cunctus pelagi cecidit fragor, aequora postquam&lt;br /&gt; prospiciens
genitor caeloque invectus aperto&lt;br /&gt; flectit equos, curruque volans
dat lora secundo.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;So he speaks, and swifter than his speech, he calms the swollen
sea,
&lt;br /&gt;scatters the gathered cloud, and brings back the sun.
&lt;br /&gt;Cymothoë and Triton, working together, thrust the ships
&lt;br /&gt;from the sharp reef: Neptune himself raises them with his trident,
&lt;br /&gt;parts the vast quicksand, tempers the flood,
&lt;br /&gt;and glides on weightless wheels, over the tops of the waves.
&lt;br /&gt;As often, when rebellion breaks out in a great nation,
&lt;br /&gt;and the common rabble rage with passion, and soon stones
&lt;br /&gt;and fiery torches fly (frenzy supplying weapons),
&lt;br /&gt;if they then see a man of great virtue, and weighty service,
&lt;br /&gt;they are silent, and stand there listening attentively:
&lt;br /&gt;he sways their passions with his words and soothes their hearts:
&lt;br /&gt;so all the uproar of the ocean died, as soon as their father,
&lt;br /&gt;gazing over the water, carried through the clear sky, wheeled
&lt;br /&gt;his horses, and gave them their head, flying behind in his
chariot.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Defessi Aeneadae, quae proxima litora, cursu&lt;br /&gt; contendunt petere,
et Libyae vertuntur ad oras.&lt;br /&gt; Est in secessu longo locus: insula
portum
&lt;br /&gt; efficit obiectu laterum, quibus omnis ab alto&lt;br /&gt; frangitur
inque sinus scindit sese unda reductos.&lt;br /&gt; Hinc atque hinc vastae
rupes geminique minantur&lt;br /&gt; in caelum scopuli, quorum sub vertice
late
&lt;br /&gt; aequora tuta silent; tum silvis scaena coruscis&lt;br /&gt; desuper
horrentique atrum nemus imminet umbra.&lt;br /&gt; Fronte sub adversa scopulis
pendentibus antrum,&lt;br /&gt; intus aquae dulces vivoque sedilia saxo,
&lt;br /&gt; nympharum domus: hic fessas non vincula navis&lt;br /&gt; ulla tenent,
unco non alligat ancora morsu.&lt;br /&gt; Huc septem Aeneas collectis
navibus omni&lt;br /&gt; ex numero subit; ac magno telluris amore&lt;br /&gt; egressi
optata potiuntur Troes harena,&lt;br /&gt; et sale tabentis artus in litore
ponunt.
&lt;br /&gt; Ac primum silici scintillam excudit Achates,&lt;br /&gt; succepitque
ignem foliis, atque arida circum&lt;br /&gt; nutrimenta dedit, rapuitque
in fomite flammam.&lt;br /&gt; Tum Cererem corruptam undis Cerealiaque
arma
&lt;br /&gt; expediunt fessi rerum, frugesque receptas&lt;br /&gt; et torrere parant
flammis et frangere saxo.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The weary followers of Aeneas made efforts to set a course
&lt;br /&gt;for the nearest land, and tacked towards the Libyan coast.
&lt;br /&gt;There is a place there in a deep inlet: an island forms a harbour
&lt;br /&gt;with the barrier of its bulk, on which every wave from the
deep
&lt;br /&gt;breaks, and divides into diminishing ripples.
&lt;br /&gt;On this side and that, vast cliffs and twin crags loom in the
sky,
&lt;br /&gt;under whose summits the whole sea is calm, far and wide:
&lt;br /&gt;then, above that, is a scene of glittering woods,
&lt;br /&gt;and a dark grove overhangs the water, with leafy shade:
&lt;br /&gt;under the headland opposite is a cave, curtained with rock,
&lt;br /&gt;inside it, fresh water, and seats of natural stone,
&lt;br /&gt;the home of Nymphs. No hawsers moor the weary ships
&lt;br /&gt;here, no anchor, with its hooked flukes, fastens them.
&lt;br /&gt;Aeneas takes shelter here with seven ships gathered
&lt;br /&gt;from the fleet, and the Trojans, with a passion for dry land,
&lt;br /&gt;disembarking, take possession of the sands they longed for,
&lt;br /&gt;and stretch their brine-caked bodies on the shore.
&lt;br /&gt;At once Achates strikes a spark from his flint,
&lt;br /&gt;catches the fire in the leaves, places dry fuel round it,
&lt;br /&gt;and quickly has flames among the kindling.
&lt;br /&gt;Then, wearied by events, they take out wheat, damaged
&lt;br /&gt;by the sea, and implements of Ceres, and prepare to parch
&lt;br /&gt;the grain over the flames, and grind it on stone.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Aeneas scopulum interea conscendit, et omnem&lt;br /&gt; prospectum late
pelago petit, Anthea si quem&lt;br /&gt; iactatum vento videat Phrygiasque
biremis,
&lt;br /&gt; aut Capyn, aut celsis in puppibus arma Caici.&lt;br /&gt; Navem in
conspectu nullam, tris litore cervos&lt;br /&gt; prospicit errantis; hos
tota armenta sequuntur&lt;br /&gt; a tergo, et longum per vallis pascitur
agmen.
&lt;br /&gt; Constitit hic, arcumque manu celerisque sagittas&lt;br /&gt; corripuit,
fidus quae tela gerebat Achates;&lt;br /&gt; ductoresque ipsos primum,
capita alta ferentis&lt;br /&gt; cornibus arboreis, sternit, tum volgus,
et omnem&lt;br /&gt; miscet agens telis nemora inter frondea turbam;&lt;br /&gt;                nec prius absistit, quam septem ingentia victor&lt;br /&gt; corpora fundat
humi, et numerum cum navibus aequet.&lt;br /&gt; Hinc portum petit, et
socios partitur in omnes.&lt;br /&gt; Vina bonus quae deinde cadis onerarat
Acestes
&lt;br /&gt; litore Trinacrio dederatque abeuntibus heros,&lt;br /&gt; dividit,
et dictis maerentia pectora mulcet:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Aeneas climbs a crag meanwhile, and searches the whole prospect
&lt;br /&gt;far and wide over the sea, looking if he can see anything
&lt;br /&gt;of Antheus and his storm-tossed Phrygian galleys,
&lt;br /&gt;or Capys, or Caicus’s arms blazoned on a high stern.
&lt;br /&gt;There’s no ship in sight: he sees three stags wandering
&lt;br /&gt;on the shore: whole herds of deer follow at their back,
&lt;br /&gt;and graze in long lines along the valley.
&lt;br /&gt;He halts at this, and grasps in his hand his bow
&lt;br /&gt;and swift arrows, shafts that loyal Achates carries,
&lt;br /&gt;and first he shoots the leaders themselves, their heads,
&lt;br /&gt;with branching antlers, held high, then the mass, with his
shafts,
&lt;br /&gt;and drives the whole crowd in confusion among the leaves:
&lt;br /&gt;The conqueror does not stop until he’s scattered seven huge
&lt;br /&gt;carcasses on the ground, equal in number to his ships.
&lt;br /&gt;Then he seeks the harbour, and divides them among all his friends.
&lt;br /&gt;Next he shares out the wine that the good Acestes had stowed
&lt;br /&gt;in jars, on the Trinacrian coast, and that hero had given them
&lt;br /&gt;on leaving: and speaking to them, calmed their sad hearts:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;'O socii&amp;#151;neque enim ignari sumus ante malorum&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt; O
passi graviora, dabit deus his quoque finem.&lt;br /&gt; Vos et Scyllaeam
rabiem penitusque sonantis&lt;br /&gt; accestis scopulos, vos et Cyclopea
saxa
&lt;br /&gt; experti: revocate animos, maestumque timorem&lt;br /&gt; mittite:
forsan et haec olim meminisse iuvabit.&lt;br /&gt; Per varios casus, per
tot discrimina rerum&lt;br /&gt; tendimus in Latium; sedes ubi fata quietas&lt;br /&gt;                ostendunt; illic fas regna resurgere Troiae.&lt;br /&gt; Durate, et vosmet
rebus servate secundis.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;‘O friends (well, we were not unknown to trouble before)
&lt;br /&gt;O you who’ve endured worse, the god will grant an end to this
too.
&lt;br /&gt;You’ve faced rabid Scylla, and her deep-sounding cliffs:
&lt;br /&gt;and you’ve experienced the Cyclopes’s rocks:
&lt;br /&gt;remember your courage and chase away gloomy fears:
&lt;br /&gt;perhaps one day you’ll even delight in remembering this.
&lt;br /&gt;Through all these misfortunes, these dangerous times,
&lt;br /&gt;we head for Latium, where the fates hold peaceful lives
&lt;br /&gt;for us: there Troy’s kingdom can rise again. Endure,
&lt;br /&gt;and preserve yourselves for happier days.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Talia voce refert, curisque ingentibus aeger&lt;br /&gt; spem voltu simulat,
premit altum corde dolorem.&lt;br /&gt; Illi se praedae accingunt, dapibusque
futuris;
&lt;br /&gt; tergora deripiunt costis et viscera nudant;&lt;br /&gt; pars in frusta
secant veribusque trementia figunt;
&lt;br /&gt; litore aena locant alii, flammasque ministrant.&lt;br /&gt; Tum victu
revocant vires, fusique per herbam&lt;br /&gt; implentur veteris Bacchi
pinguisque ferinae.&lt;br /&gt; Postquam exempta fames epulis mensaeque
remotae,
&lt;br /&gt; amissos longo socios sermone requirunt,&lt;br /&gt; spemque metumque
inter dubii, seu vivere credant,&lt;br /&gt; sive extrema pati nec iam
exaudire vocatos.&lt;br /&gt; Praecipue pius Aeneas nunc acris Oronti,
&lt;br /&gt; nunc Amyci casum gemit et crudelia secum&lt;br /&gt; fata Lyci, fortemque
Gyan, fortemque Cloanthum.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;So his voice utters, and sick with the weight of care, he pretends
&lt;br /&gt;hope, in his look, and stifles the pain deep in his heart.
&lt;br /&gt;They make ready the game, and the future feast:
&lt;br /&gt;they flay the hides from the ribs and lay the flesh bare:
&lt;br /&gt;some cut it in pieces, quivering, and fix it on spits,
&lt;br /&gt;others place cauldrons on the beach, and feed them with flames.
&lt;br /&gt;Then they revive their strength with food, stretched on the
grass,
&lt;br /&gt;and fill themselves with rich venison and old wine.
&lt;br /&gt;When hunger is quenched by the feast, and the remnants cleared,
&lt;br /&gt;deep in conversation, they discuss their missing friends,
&lt;br /&gt;and, between hope and fear, question whether they live,
&lt;br /&gt;or whether they’ve suffered death and no longer hear their
name.
&lt;br /&gt; Aeneas, the virtuous, above all mourns the lot of fierce Orontes,
&lt;br /&gt;then that of Amycus, together with Lycus’s cruel fate,
&lt;br /&gt;and those of brave Gyus, and brave Cloanthus.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Et iam finis erat, cum Iuppiter aethere summo&lt;br /&gt; despiciens mare
velivolum terrasque iacentis&lt;br /&gt; litoraque et latos populos, sic
vertice caeli
&lt;br /&gt; constitit, et Libyae defixit lumina regnis.&lt;br /&gt; Atque illum
talis iactantem pectore curas&lt;br /&gt; tristior et lacrimis oculos suffusa
nitentis
&lt;br /&gt; adloquitur Venus: 'O qui res hominumque deumque
&lt;br /&gt; aeternis regis imperiis, et fulmine terres,&lt;br /&gt; quid meus
Aeneas in te committere tantum,&lt;br /&gt; quid Troes potuere, quibus,
tot funera passis,&lt;br /&gt; cunctus ob Italiam terrarum clauditur orbis?&lt;br /&gt;                Certe hinc Romanos olim, volventibus annis,&lt;br /&gt; hinc fore ductores,
revocato a sanguine Teucri,&lt;br /&gt; qui mare, qui terras omni dicione
tenerent,
&lt;br /&gt; pollicitus, quae te, genitor, sententia vertit?&lt;br /&gt; Hoc equidem
occasum Troiae tristisque ruinas&lt;br /&gt; solabar, fatis contraria fata
rependens;
&lt;br /&gt; nunc eadem fortuna viros tot casibus actos
&lt;br /&gt; insequitur. Quem das finem, rex magne, laborum?&lt;br /&gt; Antenor
potuit, mediis elapsus Achivis,&lt;br /&gt; Illyricos penetrare sinus,
atque intima tutus&lt;br /&gt; regna Liburnorum, et fontem superare Timavi,&lt;br /&gt;                unde per ora novem vasto cum murmure montis&lt;br /&gt; it mare proruptum
et pelago premit arva sonanti.&lt;br /&gt; Hic tamen ille urbem Patavi
sedesque locavit&lt;br /&gt; Teucrorum, et genti nomen dedit, armaque fixit&lt;br /&gt;                Troia; nunc placida compostus pace quiescit:&lt;br /&gt; nos, tua progenies,
caeli quibus adnuis arcem,&lt;br /&gt; navibus (infandum!) amissis, unius
ob iram&lt;br /&gt; prodimur atque Italis longe disiungimur oris.&lt;br /&gt; Hic
pietatis honos? Sic nos in sceptra reponis?'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Now, all was complete, when Jupiter, from the heights of the air,
&lt;br /&gt;looked down on the sea with its flying sails, and the broad
lands,
&lt;br /&gt;and the coasts, and the people far and wide, and paused,
&lt;br /&gt;at the summit of heaven, and fixed his eyes on the Libyan kingdom.
&lt;br /&gt;And as he weighed such cares as he had in his heart, Venus
spoke
&lt;br /&gt;to him, sadder still, her bright eyes brimming with tears:
&lt;br /&gt;‘Oh you who rule things human, and divine, with eternal law,
&lt;br /&gt;and who terrify them all with your lightning-bolt,
&lt;br /&gt;what can my Aeneas have done to you that’s so serious,
&lt;br /&gt;what have the Trojans done, who’ve suffered so much destruction,
&lt;br /&gt;to whom the whole world’s closed, because of the Italian lands?
&lt;br /&gt;Surely you promised that at some point, as the years rolled
by,
&lt;br /&gt;the Romans would rise from them, leaders would rise,
&lt;br /&gt;restored from Teucer’s blood, who would hold power
&lt;br /&gt; over the sea, and all the lands. Father, what thought has
changed
&lt;br /&gt;your mind? It consoled me for the fall of Troy, and its sad
ruin,
&lt;br /&gt;weighing one destiny, indeed, against opposing destinies:
&lt;br /&gt;now the same misfortune follows these men driven on by such
&lt;br /&gt;disasters. Great king, what end to their efforts will you give?
&lt;br /&gt;Antenor could escape through the thick of the Greek army,
&lt;br /&gt;and safely enter the Illyrian gulfs, and deep into the realms
&lt;br /&gt;of the Liburnians, and pass the founts of Timavus,
&lt;br /&gt; from which the river bursts, with a huge mountainous roar,
&lt;br /&gt;through nine mouths, and buries the fields under its noisy
flood.
&lt;br /&gt;Here, nonetheless, he sited the city of Padua, and homes
&lt;br /&gt;for Teucrians, and gave the people a name, and hung up
&lt;br /&gt;the arms of Troy: now he’s calmly settled, in tranquil peace.
&lt;br /&gt;But we, your race, to whom you permit the heights of heaven,
&lt;br /&gt;lose our ships (shameful!), betrayed, because of one person’s
anger,
&lt;br /&gt;and kept far away from the shores of Italy.
&lt;br /&gt;Is this the prize for virtue? Is this how you restore our rule?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Olli subridens hominum sator atque deorum,&lt;br /&gt; voltu, quo caelum
tempestatesque serenat,
&lt;br /&gt; oscula libavit natae, dehinc talia fatur:&lt;br /&gt; 'Parce metu,
Cytherea: manent immota tuorum&lt;br /&gt; fata tibi; cernes urbem et promissa
Lavini
&lt;br /&gt; moenia, sublimemque feres ad sidera caeli&lt;br /&gt; magnanimum Aenean;
neque me sententia vertit.
&lt;br /&gt; Hic tibi (fabor enim, quando haec te cura remordet,&lt;br /&gt; longius
et volvens fatorum arcana movebo)&lt;br /&gt; bellum ingens geret Italia,
populosque feroces&lt;br /&gt; contundet, moresque viris et moenia ponet,
&lt;br /&gt; tertia dum Latio regnantem viderit aestas,&lt;br /&gt; ternaque transierint
Rutulis hiberna subactis.&lt;br /&gt; At puer Ascanius, cui nunc cognomen
Iulo
&lt;br /&gt; additur,&amp;#151;Ilus erat, dum res stetit Ilia regno,&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt;                triginta magnos volvendis mensibus orbis&lt;br /&gt; imperio explebit,
regnumque ab sede Lavini&lt;br /&gt; transferet, et longam multa vi muniet
Albam.
&lt;br /&gt; Hic iam ter centum totos regnabitur annos
&lt;br /&gt; gente sub Hectorea, donec regina sacerdos,&lt;br /&gt; Marte gravis,
geminam partu dabit Ilia prolem.&lt;br /&gt; Inde lupae fulvo nutricis
tegmine laetus&lt;br /&gt; Romulus excipiet gentem, et Mavortia condet&lt;br /&gt;                moenia, Romanosque suo de nomine dicet.&lt;br /&gt; His ego nec metas rerum
nec tempora pono;&lt;br /&gt; imperium sine fine dedi. Quin aspera Iuno,&lt;br /&gt;                quae mare nunc terrasque metu caelumque fatigat,&lt;br /&gt; consilia in
melius referet, mecumque fovebit&lt;br /&gt; Romanos rerum dominos gentemque
togatam:
&lt;br /&gt; sic placitum. Veniet lustris labentibus aetas,&lt;br /&gt; cum domus
Assaraci Phthiam clarasque Mycenas&lt;br /&gt; servitio premet, ac victis
dominabitur Argis.&lt;br /&gt; Nascetur pulchra Troianus origine Caesar,
&lt;br /&gt; imperium oceano, famam qui terminet astris,&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt; Iulius,
a magno demissum nomen Iulo.&lt;br /&gt; Hunc tu olim caelo, spoliis Orientis
onustum,
&lt;br /&gt; accipies secura; vocabitur hic quoque votis.&lt;br /&gt; Aspera tum
positis mitescent saecula bellis;&lt;br /&gt; cana Fides, et Vesta, Remo
cum fratre Quirinus,&lt;br /&gt; iura dabunt; dirae ferro et compagibus
artis
&lt;br /&gt; claudentur Belli portae; Furor impius intus,&lt;br /&gt; saeva sedens
super arma, et centum vinctus aenis&lt;br /&gt; post tergum nodis, fremet
horridus ore cruento.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;The father of men and gods, smiled at her with that look
&lt;br /&gt;with which he clears the sky of storms,
&lt;br /&gt;kissed his daughter’s lips, and then said this:
&lt;br /&gt; ‘Don’t be afraid, Cytherea, your child’s fate remains unaltered:
&lt;br /&gt;You’ll see the city of Lavinium, and the walls I promised,
&lt;br /&gt;and you’ll raise great-hearted Aeneas high, to the starry sky:
&lt;br /&gt;No thought has changed my mind. This son of yours
&lt;br /&gt;(since this trouble gnaws at my heart, I’ll speak,
&lt;br /&gt;and unroll the secret scroll of destiny)
&lt;br /&gt;will wage a mighty war in Italy, destroy proud peoples,
&lt;br /&gt;and establish laws, and city walls, for his warriors,
&lt;br /&gt;until a third summer sees his reign in Latium, and
&lt;br /&gt;three winter camps pass since the Rutulians were beaten.
&lt;br /&gt;But the boy Ascanius, surnamed Iulus now (He was Ilus
&lt;br /&gt;while the Ilian kingdom was a reality) will imperially
&lt;br /&gt;complete thirty great circles of the turning months,
&lt;br /&gt;and transfer his throne from its site at Lavinium,
&lt;br /&gt;and mighty in power, will build the walls of Alba Longa.
&lt;br /&gt;Here kings of Hector’s race will reign now
&lt;br /&gt;for three hundred years complete, until a royal priestess,
&lt;br /&gt;Ilia, heavy with child, shall bear Mars twins.
&lt;br /&gt;Then Romulus will further the race, proud in his nurse
&lt;br /&gt;the she-wolf’s tawny pelt, and found the walls of Mars,
&lt;br /&gt;and call the people Romans, from his own name.
&lt;br /&gt;I’ve fixed no limits or duration to their possessions:
&lt;br /&gt;I’ve given them empire without end. Why, harsh Juno
&lt;br /&gt;who now torments land, and sea and sky with fear,
&lt;br /&gt;will respond to better judgement, and favour the Romans,
&lt;br /&gt;masters of the world, and people of the toga, with me.
&lt;br /&gt;So it is decreed. A time will come, as the years glide by,
&lt;br /&gt;when the Trojan house of Assaracus will force Phthia
&lt;br /&gt;into slavery, and be lords of beaten Argos.
&lt;br /&gt;From this glorious source a Trojan Caesar will be born,
&lt;br /&gt;who will bound the empire with Ocean, his fame with the stars,
&lt;br /&gt;Augustus, a Julius, his name descended from the great Iulus.
&lt;br /&gt;You, no longer anxious, will receive him one day in heaven,
&lt;br /&gt;burdened with Eastern spoils: he’ll be called to in prayer.
&lt;br /&gt;Then with wars abandoned, the harsh ages will grow mild:
&lt;br /&gt;White haired Trust, and Vesta, Quirinus with his brother Remus
&lt;br /&gt;will make the laws: the gates of War, grim with iron,
&lt;br /&gt;and narrowed by bars, will be closed: inside impious Rage will
roar
&lt;br /&gt;frighteningly from blood-stained mouth, seated on savage weapons,
&lt;br /&gt;hands tied behind his back, with a hundred knots of bronze.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Haec ait, et Maia genitum demittit ab alto,&lt;br /&gt; ut terrae, utque
novae pateant Karthaginis arces&lt;br /&gt; hospitio Teucris, ne fati nescia
Dido
&lt;br /&gt; finibus arceret: volat ille per aera magnum&lt;br /&gt; remigio alarum,
ac Libyae citus adstitit oris.&lt;br /&gt; Et iam iussa facit, ponuntque
ferocia Poeni&lt;br /&gt; corda volente deo; in primis regina quietum
&lt;br /&gt; accipit in Teucros animum mentemque benignam.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Saying this, he sends Mercury, Maia’s son, down from heaven,
&lt;br /&gt;so that the country and strongholds of this new Carthage
&lt;br /&gt;would open to the Trojans, as guests, and Dido, unaware of
fate,
&lt;br /&gt;would not keep them from her territory. He flies through the
air
&lt;br /&gt;with a beating of mighty wings and quickly lands on Libyan
shore.
&lt;br /&gt;And soon does as commanded, and the Phoenicians set aside
&lt;br /&gt;their savage instincts, by the god’s will: the queen above
all
&lt;br /&gt;adopts calm feelings, and kind thoughts, towards the Trojans.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt; At pius Aeneas, per noctem plurima volvens,&lt;br /&gt; ut primum lux
alma data est, exire locosque&lt;br /&gt; explorare novos, quas vento accesserit
oras,
&lt;br /&gt; qui teneant, nam inculta videt, hominesne feraene,
&lt;br /&gt; quaerere constituit, sociisque exacta referre&lt;br /&gt; Classem
in convexo nemorum sub rupe cavata&lt;br /&gt; arboribus clausam circum
atque horrentibus umbris&lt;br /&gt; occulit; ipse uno graditur comitatus
Achate,
&lt;br /&gt; bina manu lato crispans hastilia ferro.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt; But Aeneas, the virtuous, turning things over all night,
&lt;br /&gt;decides, as soon as kindly dawn appears, to go out
&lt;br /&gt;and explore the place, to find what shores he has reached,
&lt;br /&gt;on the wind, who owns them (since he sees desert)
&lt;br /&gt;man or beast, and bring back the details to his friends.
&lt;br /&gt;He conceals the boats in over-hanging woods
&lt;br /&gt;under an arching cliff, enclosed by trees
&lt;br /&gt;and leafy shadows: accompanied only by Achetes,
&lt;br /&gt;he goes, swinging two broad-bladed spears in his hand.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Cui mater media sese tulit obvia silva,&lt;br /&gt; virginis os habitumque
gerens, et virginis arma&lt;br /&gt; Spartanae, vel qualis equos Threissa
fatigat
&lt;br /&gt; Harpalyce, volucremque fuga praevertitur Hebrum.&lt;br /&gt; Namque
umeris de more habilem suspenderat arcum&lt;br /&gt; venatrix, dederatque
comam diffundere ventis,&lt;br /&gt; nuda genu, nodoque sinus collecta
fluentis.
&lt;br /&gt; Ac prior, 'Heus' inquit 'iuvenes, monstrate mearum&lt;br /&gt; vidistis
si quam hic errantem forte sororum,&lt;br /&gt; succinctam pharetra et
maculosae tegmine lyncis,&lt;br /&gt; aut spumantis apri cursum clamore
prementem.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;His mother met him herself, among the trees, with the face
&lt;br /&gt;and appearance of a virgin, and a virgin’s weapons,
&lt;br /&gt;a Spartan girl, or such as Harpalyce of Thrace,
&lt;br /&gt;who wearies horses, and outdoes winged Hebrus in flight.
&lt;br /&gt;For she’d slung her bow from her shoulders, at the ready,
&lt;br /&gt;like a huntress, and loosed her hair for the wind to scatter,
&lt;br /&gt;her knees bare, and her flowing tunic gathered up in a knot.
&lt;br /&gt;And she cried first: ‘Hello, you young men, tell me,
&lt;br /&gt;if you’ve seen my sister wandering here by any chance,
&lt;br /&gt;wearing a quiver, and the hide of a dappled lynx,
&lt;br /&gt;or shouting, hot on the track of a slavering boar?’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Sic Venus; et Veneris contra sic filius orsus:&lt;br /&gt; 'Nulla tuarum
audita mihi neque visa sororum&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt; O quam te memorem, virgo?
Namque haud tibi voltus&lt;br /&gt; mortalis, nec vox hominem sonat: O,
dea certe&amp;#151;&lt;br /&gt; an Phoebi soror? an nympharum sanguinis una?&amp;#151;
&lt;br /&gt; sis felix, nostrumque leves, quaecumque, laborem,&lt;br /&gt; et,
quo sub caelo tandem, quibus orbis in oris&lt;br /&gt; iactemur, doceas.
Ignari hominumque locorumque&lt;br /&gt; erramus, vento huc vastis et fluctibus
acti:
&lt;br /&gt; multa tibi ante aras nostra cadet hostia dextra.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So Venus: and so Venus’s son began in answer:
&lt;br /&gt;‘I’ve not seen or heard any of your sisters, O Virgin –
&lt;br /&gt;or how should I name you? Since your looks are not mortal
&lt;br /&gt;and your voice is more than human: oh, a goddess for certain!
&lt;br /&gt;Or Phoebus’s sister? Or one of the race of Nymphs?
&lt;br /&gt;Be kind, whoever you may be, and lighten our labour,
&lt;br /&gt;and tell us only what sky we’re under, and what shores
&lt;br /&gt;we’ve landed on: we’re adrift here, driven by wind and vast
seas,
&lt;br /&gt;knowing nothing of the people or the country:
&lt;br /&gt;many a sacrifice to you will fall at the altars, under our
hand.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Tum Venus: 'Haud equidem tali me dignor honore;&lt;br /&gt; virginibus
Tyriis mos est gestare pharetram,&lt;br /&gt; purpureoque alte suras vincire
cothurno.
&lt;br /&gt; Punica regna vides, Tyrios et Agenoris urbem;&lt;br /&gt; sed fines
Libyci, genus intractabile bello.&lt;br /&gt; Imperium Dido Tyria regit
urbe profecta,&lt;br /&gt; germanum fugiens. Longa est iniuria, longae&lt;br /&gt;                ambages; sed summa sequar fastigia rerum.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Then Venus said: ‘I don’t think myself worthy of such honours:
&lt;br /&gt;it’s the custom of Tyrian girls to carry a quiver,
&lt;br /&gt;and lace our calves high up, over red hunting boots.
&lt;br /&gt;You see the kingdom of Carthage, Tyrians, Agenor’s city:
&lt;br /&gt;but bordered by Libyans, a people formidable in war.
&lt;br /&gt;Dido rules this empire, having set out from Tyre,
&lt;br /&gt;fleeing her brother. It’s a long tale of wrong, with many
&lt;br /&gt;windings: but I’ll trace the main chapters of the story.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;'Huic coniunx Sychaeus erat, ditissimus agri&lt;br /&gt; Phoenicum, et
magno miserae dilectus amore,&lt;br /&gt; cui pater intactam dederat, primisque
iugarat
&lt;br /&gt; ominibus. Sed regna Tyri germanus habebat&lt;br /&gt; Pygmalion, scelere
ante alios immanior omnes.&lt;br /&gt; Quos inter medius venit furor. Ille
Sychaeum
&lt;br /&gt; impius ante aras, atque auri caecus amore,
&lt;br /&gt; clam ferro incautum superat, securus amorum&lt;br /&gt; germanae;
factumque diu celavit, et aegram,&lt;br /&gt; multa malus simulans, vana
spe lusit amantem.&lt;br /&gt; Ipsa sed in somnis inhumati venit imago&lt;br /&gt;                coniugis, ora modis attollens pallida miris,&lt;br /&gt; crudeles aras
traiectaque pectora ferro&lt;br /&gt; nudavit, caecumque domus scelus omne
retexit.
&lt;br /&gt; Tum celerare fugam patriaque excedere suadet,&lt;br /&gt; auxiliumque
viae veteres tellure recludit&lt;br /&gt; thesauros, ignotum argenti pondus
et auri.&lt;br /&gt; His commota fugam Dido sociosque parabat:&lt;br /&gt; conveniunt,
quibus aut odium crudele tyranni&lt;br /&gt; aut metus acer erat; navis,
quae forte paratae,&lt;br /&gt; corripiunt, onerantque auro: portantur
avari
&lt;br /&gt; Pygmalionis opes pelago; dux femina facti.&lt;br /&gt; Devenere locos,
ubi nunc ingentia cernis&lt;br /&gt; moenia surgentemque novae Karthaginis
arcem,
&lt;br /&gt; mercatique solum, facti de nomine Byrsam,
&lt;br /&gt; taurino quantum possent circumdare tergo.&lt;br /&gt; Sed vos qui
tandem, quibus aut venistis ab oris,&lt;br /&gt; quove tenetis iter? 'Quaerenti
talibus ille&lt;br /&gt; suspirans, imoque trahens a pectore vocem:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sychaeus was her husband, wealthiest, in land, of Phoenicians
&lt;br /&gt;and loved with a great love by the wretched girl,
&lt;br /&gt;whose father gave her as a virgin to him, and wed them
&lt;br /&gt;with great solemnity. But her brother Pygmalion, savage
&lt;br /&gt;in wickedness beyond all others, held the kingdom of Tyre.
&lt;br /&gt;Madness came between them. The king, blinded by greed for gold,
&lt;br /&gt;killed the unwary Sychaeus, secretly, with a knife, impiously,
&lt;br /&gt;in front of the altars, indifferent to his sister’s affections.
&lt;br /&gt;He concealed his actions for a while, deceived the lovesick
girl,
&lt;br /&gt;with empty hopes, and many evil pretences.
&lt;br /&gt;But the ghost of her unburied husband came to her in dream:
&lt;br /&gt;lifting his pale head in a strange manner, he laid bare the
cruelty
&lt;br /&gt;at the altars, and his heart pierced by the knife,
&lt;br /&gt;and unveiled all the secret wickedness of that house.
&lt;br /&gt;Then he urged her to leave quickly and abandon her country,
&lt;br /&gt;and, to help her journey, revealed an ancient treasure
&lt;br /&gt;under the earth, an unknown weight of gold and silver.
&lt;br /&gt;Shaken by all this, Dido prepared her flight and her friends.
&lt;br /&gt;Those who had fierce hatred of the tyrant or bitter fear,
&lt;br /&gt;gathered together: they seized some ships that by chance
&lt;br /&gt;were ready, and loaded the gold: greedy Pygmalion’s riches
&lt;br /&gt;are carried overseas: a woman leads the enterprise.
&lt;br /&gt;The came to this place, and bought land, where you now see
&lt;br /&gt;the vast walls, and resurgent stronghold, of new Carthage,
&lt;br /&gt;as much as they could enclose with the strips of hide
&lt;br /&gt;from a single bull, and from that they called it Byrsa.
&lt;br /&gt;But who then are you? What shores do you come from?
&lt;br /&gt;What course do you take?’ He sighed as she questioned him,
&lt;br /&gt;and drawing the words from deep in his heart he replied:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;'O dea, si prima repetens ab origine pergam,&lt;br /&gt; et vacet annalis
nostrorum audire laborum,&lt;br /&gt; ante diem clauso componat Vesper
Olympo.
&lt;br /&gt; Nos Troia antiqua, si vestras forte per auris&lt;br /&gt; Troiae nomen
iit, diversa per aequora vectos&lt;br /&gt; forte sua Libycis tempestas
adpulit oris.&lt;br /&gt; Sum pius Aeneas, raptos qui ex hoste Penates
&lt;br /&gt; classe veho mecum, fama super aethera notus.&lt;br /&gt; Italiam quaero
patriam et genus ab Iove summo.&lt;br /&gt; Bis denis Phrygium conscendi
navibus aequor,&lt;br /&gt; matre dea monstrante viam, data fata secutus;&lt;br /&gt;                vix septem convolsae undis Euroque supersunt.&lt;br /&gt; Ipse ignotus,
egens, Libyae deserta peragro,&lt;br /&gt; Europa atque Asia pulsus.' Nec
plura querentem&lt;br /&gt; passa Venus medio sic interfata dolore est:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;‘O goddess, if I were to start my tale at the very beginning,
&lt;br /&gt;and you had time to hear the story of our misfortunes,
&lt;br /&gt;Vesper would have shut day away in the closed heavens.
&lt;br /&gt;A storm drove us at whim to Libya’s shores,
&lt;br /&gt;sailing the many seas from ancient Troy,
&lt;br /&gt;if by chance the name of Troy has come to your hearing.
&lt;br /&gt;I am that Aeneas, the virtuous, who carries my household gods
&lt;br /&gt;in my ship with me, having snatched them from the enemy,
&lt;br /&gt;my name is known beyond the sky.
&lt;br /&gt;I seek my country Italy, and a people born of Jupiter on high.
&lt;br /&gt;I embarked on the Phrygian sea with twenty ships,
&lt;br /&gt;following my given fate, my mother, a goddess, showing the
way:
&lt;br /&gt;barely seven are left, wrenched from the wind and waves.
&lt;br /&gt;I myself wander, destitute and unknown, in the Libyan desert,
&lt;br /&gt;driven from Europe and Asia.’ Venus did not wait
&lt;br /&gt;for further complaint but broke in on his lament like this:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;'Quisquis es, haud, credo, invisus caelestibus auras&lt;br /&gt; vitalis
carpis, Tyriam qui adveneris urbem.&lt;br /&gt; Perge modo, atque hinc
te reginae ad limina perfer,&lt;br /&gt; Namque tibi reduces socios classemque
relatam
&lt;br /&gt; nuntio, et in tutum versis aquilonibus actam,&lt;br /&gt; ni frustra
augurium vani docuere parentes.&lt;br /&gt; Aspice bis senos laetantis
agmine cycnos,&lt;br /&gt; aetheria quos lapsa plaga Iovis ales aperto
&lt;br /&gt; turbabat caelo; nunc terras ordine longo&lt;br /&gt; aut capere, aut
captas iam despectare videntur:&lt;br /&gt; ut reduces illi ludunt stridentibus
alis,
&lt;br /&gt; et coetu cinxere polum, cantusque dedere,&lt;br /&gt; haud aliter
puppesque tuae pubesque tuorum&lt;br /&gt; aut portum tenet aut pleno subit
ostia velo.&lt;br /&gt; Perge modo, et, qua te ducit via, dirige gressum.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;‘Whoever you are I don’t think you draw the breath of life
&lt;br /&gt;while hated by the gods, you who’ve reached a city of Tyre.
&lt;br /&gt;Only go on from here, and take yourself to the queen’s threshold,
&lt;br /&gt;since I bring you news that your friends are restored,
&lt;br /&gt;and your ships recalled, driven to safety by the shifting winds,
&lt;br /&gt;unless my parents taught me false prophecies, in vain.
&lt;br /&gt;See, those twelve swans in exultant line, that an eagle,
&lt;br /&gt;Jupiter’s bird, swooping from the heavens,
&lt;br /&gt;was troubling in the clear sky: now, in a long file, they seem
&lt;br /&gt;to have settled, or be gazing down now at those who already
have.
&lt;br /&gt;As, returning, their wings beat in play, and they circle the
zenith
&lt;br /&gt;in a crowd, and give their cry, so your ships and your people
&lt;br /&gt;are in harbour, or near its entrance under full sail.
&lt;br /&gt;Only go on, turn your steps where the path takes you.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Dixit, et avertens rosea cervice refulsit,&lt;br /&gt; ambrosiaeque comae
divinum vertice odorem&lt;br /&gt; spiravere, pedes vestis defluxit ad
imos,
&lt;br /&gt; et vera incessu patuit dea. Ille ubi matrem&lt;br /&gt; adgnovit,
tali fugientem est voce secutus:&lt;br /&gt; 'Quid natum totiens, crudelis
tu quoque, falsis&lt;br /&gt; ludis imaginibus? Cur dextrae iungere dextram&lt;br /&gt;                non datur, ac veras audire et reddere voces?'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;She spoke, and turning away she reflected the light
&lt;br /&gt;from her rose-tinted neck, and breathed a divine perfume
&lt;br /&gt;from her ambrosial hair: her robes trailed down to her feet,
&lt;br /&gt;and, in her step, showed her a true goddess. He recognised
&lt;br /&gt;his mother, and as she vanished followed her with his voice:
&lt;br /&gt;‘You too are cruel, why do you taunt your son with false
&lt;br /&gt;phantoms? Why am I not allowed to join hand
&lt;br /&gt;with hand, and speak and hear true words?’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Talibus incusat, gressumque ad moenia tendit:&lt;br /&gt; at Venus obscuro
gradientes aere saepsit,&lt;br /&gt; et multo nebulae circum dea fudit
amictu,
&lt;br /&gt; cernere ne quis eos, neu quis contingere posset,&lt;br /&gt; molirive
moram, aut veniendi poscere causas.&lt;br /&gt; Ipsa Paphum sublimis abit,
sedesque revisit&lt;br /&gt; laeta suas, ubi templum illi, centumque Sabaeo
&lt;br /&gt; ture calent arae, sertisque recentibus halant.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So he accuses her, and turns his steps towards the city.
&lt;br /&gt;But Venus veiled them with a dark mist as they walked,
&lt;br /&gt;and, as a goddess, spread a thick covering of cloud around
them,
&lt;br /&gt;so that no one could see them, or touch them,
&lt;br /&gt;or cause them delay, or ask them where they were going.
&lt;br /&gt;She herself soars high in the air, to Paphos, and returns to
her home
&lt;br /&gt;with delight, where her temple and its hundred altars
&lt;br /&gt;steam with Sabean incense, fragrant with fresh garlands.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Corripuere viam interea, qua semita monstrat.&lt;br /&gt; Iamque ascendebant
collem, qui plurimus urbi&lt;br /&gt; imminet, adversasque adspectat desuper
arces.
&lt;br /&gt; Miratur molem Aeneas, magalia quondam,&lt;br /&gt; miratur portas
strepitumque et strata viarum.&lt;br /&gt; Instant ardentes Tyrii pars
ducere muros,&lt;br /&gt; molirique arcem et manibus subvolvere saxa,
&lt;br /&gt; pars optare locum tecto et concludere sulco.&lt;br /&gt; [Iura magistratusque
legunt sanctumque senatum;]&lt;br /&gt; hic portus alii effodiunt; hic
alta theatris&lt;br /&gt; fundamenta locant alii, immanisque columnas
&lt;br /&gt; rupibus excidunt, scaenis decora alta futuris.&lt;br /&gt; Qualis
apes aestate nova per florea rura&lt;br /&gt; exercet sub sole labor, cum
gentis adultos&lt;br /&gt; educunt fetus, aut cum liquentia mella&lt;br /&gt; stipant
et dulci distendunt nectare cellas,&lt;br /&gt; aut onera accipiunt venientum,
aut agmine facto&lt;br /&gt; ignavom fucos pecus a praesepibus arcent:
&lt;br /&gt; fervet opus, redolentque thymo fragrantia mella.&lt;br /&gt; 'O fortunati,
quorum iam moenia surgunt!'&lt;br /&gt; Aeneas ait, et fastigia suspicit
urbis.
&lt;br /&gt; Infert se saeptus nebula, mirabile dictu,&lt;br /&gt; per medios,
miscetque viris, neque cernitur ulli.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Meanwhile they’ve tackled the route the path revealed.
&lt;br /&gt;And soon they climbed the hill that looms high over the city,
&lt;br /&gt;and looks down from above on the towers that face it.
&lt;br /&gt;Aeneas marvels at the mass of buildings, once huts,
&lt;br /&gt;marvels at the gates, the noise, the paved roads.
&lt;br /&gt;The eager Tyrians are busy, some building walls,
&lt;br /&gt;and raising the citadel, rolling up stones by hand,
&lt;br /&gt;some choosing the site for a house, and marking a furrow:
&lt;br /&gt;they make magistrates and laws, and a sacred senate:
&lt;br /&gt;here some are digging a harbour: others lay down
&lt;br /&gt;the deep foundations of a theatre, and carve huge columns
&lt;br /&gt;from the cliff, tall adornments for the future stage.
&lt;br /&gt;Just as bees in early summer carry out their tasks
&lt;br /&gt;among the flowery fields, in the sun, when they lead out
&lt;br /&gt;the adolescent young of their race, or cram the cells
&lt;br /&gt;with liquid honey, and swell them with sweet nectar,
&lt;br /&gt;or receive the incoming burdens, or forming lines
&lt;br /&gt;drive the lazy herd of drones from their hives:
&lt;br /&gt;the work glows, and the fragrant honey’s sweet with thyme.
&lt;br /&gt;‘O fortunate those whose walls already rise!’
&lt;br /&gt;Aeneas cries, and admires the summits of the city.
&lt;br /&gt;He enters among them, veiled in mist (marvellous to tell)
&lt;br /&gt;and mingles with the people seen by no one.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Lucus in urbe fuit media, laetissimus umbra,&lt;br /&gt; quo primum iactati
undis et turbine Poeni&lt;br /&gt; effodere loco signum, quod regia Iuno
&lt;br /&gt; monstrarat, caput acris equi; sic nam fore bello&lt;br /&gt; egregiam
et facilem victu per saecula gentem.&lt;br /&gt; Hic templum Iunoni ingens
Sidonia Dido&lt;br /&gt; condebat, donis opulentum et numine divae,&lt;br /&gt;                aerea cui gradibus surgebant limina, nexaeque&lt;br /&gt; aere trabes,
foribus cardo stridebat aenis.&lt;br /&gt; Hoc primum in luco nova res
oblata timorem&lt;br /&gt; leniit, hic primum Aeneas sperare salutem&lt;br /&gt;                ausus, et adflictis melius confidere rebus.&lt;br /&gt; Namque sub ingenti
lustrat dum singula templo,&lt;br /&gt; reginam opperiens, dum, quae fortuna
sit urbi,&lt;br /&gt; artificumque manus inter se operumque laborem&lt;br /&gt;                miratur, videt Iliacas ex ordine pugnas,&lt;br /&gt; bellaque iam fama
totum volgata per orbem,&lt;br /&gt; Atridas, Priamumque, et saevum ambobus
Achillem.
&lt;br /&gt; Constitit, et lacrimans, 'Quis iam locus' inquit 'Achate,
&lt;br /&gt; quae regio in terris nostri non plena laboris?&lt;br /&gt; En Priamus!
Sunt hic etiam sua praemia laudi;&lt;br /&gt; sunt lacrimae rerum et mentem
mortalia tangunt.&lt;br /&gt; Solve metus; feret haec aliquam tibi fama
salutem.'
&lt;br /&gt; Sic ait, atque animum pictura pascit inani,&lt;br /&gt; multa gemens,
largoque umectat flumine voltum.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There was a grove in the centre of the city, delightful
&lt;br /&gt;with shade, where the wave and storm-tossed Phoenicians
&lt;br /&gt;first uncovered the head of a fierce horse, that regal Juno
&lt;br /&gt;showed them: so the race would be noted in war,
&lt;br /&gt;and rich in substance throughout the ages.
&lt;br /&gt;Here Sidonian Dido was establishing a great temple
&lt;br /&gt;to Juno, rich with gifts and divine presence,
&lt;br /&gt;with bronze entrances rising from stairways, and beams
&lt;br /&gt;jointed with bronze, and hinges creaking on bronze doors.
&lt;br /&gt;Here in the grove something new appeared that calmed his fears
&lt;br /&gt;for the first time, here for the first time Aeneas dared to
hope
&lt;br /&gt;for safety, and to put greater trust in his afflicted fortunes.
&lt;br /&gt;While, waiting for the queen, in the vast temple, he looks
&lt;br /&gt;at each thing: while he marvels at the city’s wealth,
&lt;br /&gt;the skill of their artistry, and the products of their labours,
&lt;br /&gt;he sees the battles at Troy in their correct order,
&lt;br /&gt;the War, known through its fame to the whole world,
&lt;br /&gt;the sons of Atreus, of Priam, and Achilles angered with both.
&lt;br /&gt;He halted, and said, with tears: ‘What place is there,
&lt;br /&gt;Achates, what region of earth not full of our hardships?
&lt;br /&gt;See, Priam! Here too virtue has its rewards, here too
&lt;br /&gt;there are tears for events, and mortal things touch the heart.
&lt;br /&gt;Lose your fears: this fame will bring you benefit.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Namque videbat, uti bellantes Pergama circum&lt;br /&gt; hac fugerent Graii,
premeret Troiana iuventus,&lt;br /&gt; hac Phryges, instaret curru cristatus
Achilles.
&lt;br /&gt; Nec procul hinc Rhesi niveis tentoria velis&lt;br /&gt; adgnoscit
lacrimans, primo quae prodita somno&lt;br /&gt; Tydides multa vastabat
caede cruentus,&lt;br /&gt; ardentisque avertit equos in castra, prius
quam
&lt;br /&gt; pabula gustassent Troiae Xanthumque bibissent.&lt;br /&gt; Parte alia
fugiens amissis Troilus armis,&lt;br /&gt; infelix puer atque impar congressus
Achilli,
&lt;br /&gt; fertur equis, curruque haeret resupinus inani,
&lt;br /&gt; lora tenens tamen; huic cervixque comaeque trahuntur&lt;br /&gt; per
terram, et versa pulvis inscribitur hasta.&lt;br /&gt; Interea ad templum
non aequae Palladis ibant&lt;br /&gt; crinibus Iliades passis peplumque
ferebant,
&lt;br /&gt; suppliciter tristes et tunsae pectora palmis;&lt;br /&gt; diva solo
fixos oculos aversa tenebat.&lt;br /&gt; Ter circum Iliacos raptaverat
Hectora muros,&lt;br /&gt; exanimumque auro corpus vendebat Achilles.&lt;br /&gt;                Tum vero ingentem gemitum dat pectore ab imo,&lt;br /&gt; ut spolia, ut
currus, utque ipsum corpus amici,&lt;br /&gt; tendentemque manus Priamum
conspexit inermis.&lt;br /&gt; Se quoque principibus permixtum adgnovit
Achivis,
&lt;br /&gt; Eoasque acies et nigri Memnonis arma.&lt;br /&gt; Ducit Amazonidum
lunatis agmina peltis&lt;br /&gt; Penthesilea furens, mediisque in milibus
ardet,
&lt;br /&gt; aurea subnectens exsertae cingula mammae,&lt;br /&gt; bellatrix, audetque
viris concurrere virgo.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;So he speaks, and feeds his spirit with the insubstantial frieze,
&lt;br /&gt;sighing often, and his face wet with the streaming tears.
&lt;br /&gt;For he saw how, here, the Greeks fled, as they fought round
Troy,
&lt;br /&gt;chased by the Trojan youth, and, there, the Trojans fled,
&lt;br /&gt;with plumed Achilles pressing them close in his chariot.
&lt;br /&gt;Not far away, through his tears, he recognises Rhesus’s
&lt;br /&gt;white-canvassed tents, that blood-stained Diomede, Tydeus’s
son,
&lt;br /&gt;laid waste with great slaughter, betrayed in their first sleep,
&lt;br /&gt;diverting the fiery horses to his camp, before they could eat
&lt;br /&gt;Trojan fodder, or drink from the river Xanthus.
&lt;br /&gt;Elsewhere Troilus, his weapons discarded in flight,
&lt;br /&gt;unhappy boy, unequally matched in his battle with Achilles,
&lt;br /&gt;is dragged by his horses, clinging face-up to the empty chariot,
&lt;br /&gt;still clutching the reins: his neck and hair trailing
&lt;br /&gt;on the ground, and his spear reversed furrowing the dust.
&lt;br /&gt;Meanwhile the Trojan women with loose hair, walked
&lt;br /&gt;to unjust Pallas’s temple carrying the sacred robe,
&lt;br /&gt;mourning humbly, and beating their breasts with their hands.
&lt;br /&gt;The goddess was turned away, her eyes fixed on the ground.
&lt;br /&gt;Three times had Achilles dragged Hector round the walls of
Troy,
&lt;br /&gt;and now was selling the lifeless corpse for gold.
&lt;br /&gt;Then Aeneas truly heaves a deep sigh, from the depths of his
heart,
&lt;br /&gt;as he views the spoils, the chariot, the very body of his friend,
&lt;br /&gt;and Priam stretching out his unwarlike hands.
&lt;br /&gt;He recognised himself as well, fighting the Greek princes,
&lt;br /&gt;and the Ethiopian ranks and black Memnon’s armour.
&lt;br /&gt;Raging Penthesilea leads the file of Amazons,
&lt;br /&gt;with crescent shields, and shines out among her thousands,
&lt;br /&gt;her golden girdle fastened beneath her exposed breasts,
&lt;br /&gt;a virgin warrior daring to fight with men.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Haec dum Dardanio Aeneae miranda videntur,&lt;br /&gt; dum stupet, obtutuque
haeret defixus in uno,&lt;br /&gt; regina ad templum, forma pulcherrima
Dido,
&lt;br /&gt; incessit magna iuvenum stipante caterva.&lt;br /&gt; Qualis in Eurotae
ripis aut per iuga Cynthi&lt;br /&gt; exercet Diana choros, quam mille
secutae
&lt;br /&gt; hinc atque hinc glomerantur oreades; illa pharetram&lt;br /&gt; fert
umero, gradiensque deas supereminet omnis:&lt;br /&gt; Latonae tacitum
pertemptant gaudia pectus:&lt;br /&gt; talis erat Dido, talem se laeta
ferebat
&lt;br /&gt; per medios, instans operi regnisque futuris.&lt;br /&gt; Tum foribus
divae, media testudine templi,&lt;br /&gt; saepta armis, solioque alte
subnixa resedit.&lt;br /&gt; Iura dabat legesque viris, operumque laborem
&lt;br /&gt; partibus aequabat iustis, aut sorte trahebat:&lt;br /&gt; cum subito
Aeneas concursu accedere magno&lt;br /&gt; Anthea Sergestumque videt fortemque
Cloanthum,
&lt;br /&gt; Teucrorumque alios, ater quos aequore turbo
&lt;br /&gt; dispulerat penitusque alias avexerat oras.&lt;br /&gt; Obstipuit simul
ipse simul perculsus Achates&lt;br /&gt; laetitiaque metuque; avidi coniungere
dextras
&lt;br /&gt; ardebant; sed res animos incognita turbat.&lt;br /&gt; Dissimulant,
et nube cava speculantur amicti,&lt;br /&gt; quae fortuna viris, classem
quo litore linquant,&lt;br /&gt; quid veniant; cunctis nam lecti navibus
ibant,
&lt;br /&gt; orantes veniam, et templum clamore petebant.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;While these wonderful sights are viewed by Trojan Aeneas,
&lt;br /&gt;while amazed he hangs there, rapt, with fixed gaze,
&lt;br /&gt;Queen Dido, of loveliest form, reached the temple,
&lt;br /&gt;with a great crowd of youths accompanying her.
&lt;br /&gt;Just as Diana leads her dancing throng on Eurotas’s banks,
&lt;br /&gt;or along the ridges of Cynthus, and, following her,
&lt;br /&gt;a thousand mountain-nymphs gather on either side:
&lt;br /&gt;and she carries a quiver on her shoulder, and overtops
&lt;br /&gt;all the other goddesses as she walks: and delight
&lt;br /&gt;seizes her mother Latona’s silent heart:
&lt;br /&gt;such was Dido, so she carried herself, joyfully,
&lt;br /&gt;amongst them, furthering the work, and her rising kingdom.
&lt;br /&gt;Then, fenced with weapons, and resting on a high throne,
&lt;br /&gt;she took her seat, at the goddess’s doorway, under the central
vault.
&lt;br /&gt;She was giving out laws and statutes to the people, and sharing
&lt;br /&gt;the workers labour out in fair proportions, or assigning it
by lot:
&lt;br /&gt;when Aeneas suddenly saw Antheus, and Sergestus,
&lt;br /&gt;and brave Cloanthus, approaching, among a large crowd,
&lt;br /&gt;with others of the Trojans whom the black storm-clouds
&lt;br /&gt;had scattered over the sea and carried far off to other shores.
&lt;br /&gt;He was stunned, and Achates was stunned as well
&lt;br /&gt;with joy and fear: they burned with eagerness to clasp hands,
&lt;br /&gt;but the unexpected event confused their minds.
&lt;br /&gt;They stay concealed and, veiled in the deep mist, they watch
&lt;br /&gt;to see what happens to their friends, what shore they have
left
&lt;br /&gt;the fleet on, and why they are here: the elect of every ship
came
&lt;br /&gt;begging favour, and made for the temple among the shouting.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Postquam introgressi et coram data copia fandi,&lt;br /&gt; maximus Ilioneus
placido sic pectore coepit:&lt;br /&gt; 'O Regina, novam cui condere Iuppiter
urbem
&lt;br /&gt; iustitiaque dedit gentis frenare superbas,&lt;br /&gt; Troes te miseri,
ventis maria omnia vecti,&lt;br /&gt; oramus, prohibe infandos a navibus
ignis,
&lt;br /&gt; parce pio generi, et propius res aspice nostras.&lt;br /&gt; Non nos
aut ferro Libycos populare Penatis&lt;br /&gt; venimus, aut raptas ad litora
vertere praedas;&lt;br /&gt; non ea vis animo, nec tanta superbia victis.
&lt;br /&gt; Est locus, Hesperiam Grai cognomine dicunt,
&lt;br /&gt; terra antiqua, potens armis atque ubere glaebae;&lt;br /&gt; Oenotri
coluere viri; nunc fama minores&lt;br /&gt; Italiam dixisse ducis de nomine
gentem.
&lt;br /&gt; Hic cursus fuit:&lt;br /&gt; cum subito adsurgens fluctu nimbosus
Orion
&lt;br /&gt; in vada caeca tulit, penitusque procacibus austris
&lt;br /&gt; perque undas, superante salo, perque invia saxa&lt;br /&gt; dispulit;
huc pauci vestris adnavimus oris.&lt;br /&gt; Quod genus hoc hominum? Quaeve
hunc tam barbara morem&lt;br /&gt; permittit patria? Hospitio prohibemur
harenae;
&lt;br /&gt; bella cient, primaque vetant consistere terra.
&lt;br /&gt; Si genus humanum et mortalia temnitis arma&lt;br /&gt; at sperate
deos memores fandi atque nefandi.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;When they’d entered, and freedom to speak in person
&lt;br /&gt;had been granted, Ilioneus, the eldest, began calmly:
&lt;br /&gt;‘O queen, whom Jupiter grants the right to found
&lt;br /&gt;a new city, and curb proud tribes with your justice,
&lt;br /&gt;we unlucky Trojans, driven by the winds over every sea,
&lt;br /&gt;pray to you: keep the terror of fire away from our ships,
&lt;br /&gt;spare a virtuous race and look more kindly on our fate.
&lt;br /&gt;We have not come to despoil Libyan homes with the sword,
&lt;br /&gt;or to carry off stolen plunder to the shore: that violence
&lt;br /&gt;is not in our minds, the conquered have not such pride.
&lt;br /&gt;There’s a place called Hesperia by the Greeks,
&lt;br /&gt;an ancient land, strong in men, with a rich soil:
&lt;br /&gt;There the Oenotrians lived: now rumour has it
&lt;br /&gt;that a later people has called it Italy, after their leader.
&lt;br /&gt;We had set our course there when stormy Orion,
&lt;br /&gt;rising with the tide, carried us onto hidden shoals,
&lt;br /&gt;and fierce winds scattered us far, with the overwhelming surge,
&lt;br /&gt;over the waves among uninhabitable rocks:
&lt;br /&gt;we few have drifted here to your shores.
&lt;br /&gt;What race of men is this? What land is so barbaric as to allow
&lt;br /&gt;this custom, that we’re denied the hospitality of the sands?
&lt;br /&gt;They stir up war, and prevent us setting foot on dry land.
&lt;br /&gt;If you despise the human race and mortal weapons,
&lt;br /&gt;still trust that the gods remember right and wrong.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;'Rex erat Aeneas nobis, quo iustior alter,&lt;br /&gt; nec pietate fuit,
nec bello maior et armis.&lt;br /&gt; Quem si fata virum servant, si vescitur
aura
&lt;br /&gt; aetheria, neque adhuc crudelibus occubat umbris,&lt;br /&gt; non metus;
officio nec te certasse priorem&lt;br /&gt; poeniteat. Sunt et Siculis
regionibus urbes&lt;br /&gt; armaque, Troianoque a sanguine clarus Acestes.&lt;br /&gt;                Quassatam ventis liceat subducere classem,&lt;br /&gt; et silvis aptare
trabes et stringere remos:&lt;br /&gt; si datur Italiam, sociis et rege
recepto,
&lt;br /&gt; tendere, ut Italiam laeti Latiumque petamus;
&lt;br /&gt; sin absumpta salus, et te, pater optime Teucrum,&lt;br /&gt; pontus
habet Libyae, nec spes iam restat Iuli,&lt;br /&gt; at freta Sicaniae saltem
sedesque paratas,&lt;br /&gt; unde huc advecti, regemque petamus Acesten.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'Aeneas was our king, no one more just than him
&lt;br /&gt;in his duty, or greater in war and weaponry.
&lt;br /&gt;If fate still protects the man, if he still enjoys the ethereal
air,
&lt;br /&gt;if he doesn’t yet rest among the cruel shades, there’s nothing
&lt;br /&gt;to fear, and you’d not repent of vying with him first in kindness.
&lt;br /&gt;Then there are cities and fields too in the region of Sicily,
&lt;br /&gt;and famous Acestes, of Trojan blood. Allow us
&lt;br /&gt;to beach our fleet, damaged by the storms,
&lt;br /&gt;and cut planks from trees, and shape oars,
&lt;br /&gt;so if our king’s restored and our friends are found
&lt;br /&gt;we can head for Italy, gladly seek Italy and Latium:
&lt;br /&gt;and if our saviour’s lost, and the Libyan seas hold you,
&lt;br /&gt;Troy’s most virtuous father, if no hope now remains from Iulus,
&lt;br /&gt;let us seek the Sicilian straits, from which we were driven,
&lt;br /&gt;and the home prepared for us, and a king, Acestes.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; Talibus Ilioneus; cuncti simul ore fremebant&lt;br /&gt; Dardanidae.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;So Ilioneus spoke: and the Trojans all shouted with one voice.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Tum breviter Dido, voltum demissa, profatur:&lt;br /&gt; 'Solvite corde
metum, Teucri, secludite curas.&lt;br /&gt; Res dura et regni novitas me
talia cogunt
&lt;br /&gt; moliri, et late finis custode tueri.&lt;br /&gt; Quis genus Aeneadum,
quis Troiae nesciat urbem,&lt;br /&gt; virtutesque virosque, aut tanti
incendia belli?&lt;br /&gt; Non obtusa adeo gestamus pectora Poeni,
&lt;br /&gt; nec tam aversus equos Tyria Sol iungit ab urbe.&lt;br /&gt; Seu vos
Hesperiam magnam Saturniaque arva,&lt;br /&gt; sive Erycis finis regemque
optatis Acesten,&lt;br /&gt; auxilio tutos dimittam, opibusque iuvabo.
&lt;br /&gt; Voltis et his mecum pariter considere regnis;&lt;br /&gt; urbem quam
statuo vestra est, subducite navis;&lt;br /&gt; Tros Tyriusque mihi nullo
discrimine agetur.&lt;br /&gt; Atque utinam rex ipse Noto compulsus eodem
&lt;br /&gt; adforet Aeneas! Equidem per litora certos&lt;br /&gt; dimittam et
Libyae lustrare extrema iubebo,&lt;br /&gt; si quibus eiectus silvis aut
urbibus errat.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Then, Dido, spoke briefly, with lowered eyes:
&lt;br /&gt;‘Trojans, free your hearts of fear: dispel your cares.
&lt;br /&gt;Harsh events and the newness of the kingdom force me to effect
&lt;br /&gt;such things, and protect my borders with guards on all sides.
&lt;br /&gt;Who doesn’t know of Aeneas’s race, and the city of Troy,
&lt;br /&gt;the bravery, the men, or so great a blaze of warfare,
&lt;br /&gt;indeed, we Phoenicians don’t possess unfeeling hearts,
&lt;br /&gt;the sun doesn’t harness his horses that far from this Tyrian
city.
&lt;br /&gt;Whether you opt for mighty Hesperia, and Saturn’s fields,
&lt;br /&gt;or the summit of Eryx, and Acestes for king,
&lt;br /&gt;I’ll see you safely escorted, and help you with my wealth.
&lt;br /&gt;Or do you wish to settle here with me, as equals in my kingdom?
&lt;br /&gt;The city I build is yours: beach your ships:
&lt;br /&gt;Trojans and Tyrians will be treated by me without distinction.
&lt;br /&gt;I wish your king Aeneas himself were here, driven
&lt;br /&gt;by that same storm! Indeed, I’ll send reliable men
&lt;br /&gt;along the coast, and order them to travel the length of Libya,
&lt;br /&gt;in case he’s driven aground, and wandering the woods and towns.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;His animum arrecti dictis et fortis Achates&lt;br /&gt; et pater Aeneas
iamdudum erumpere nubem&lt;br /&gt; ardebant. Prior Aenean compellat Achates:
&lt;br /&gt; 'Nate dea, quae nunc animo sententia surgit?&lt;br /&gt; omnia tuta
vides, classem sociosque receptos.&lt;br /&gt; Unus abest, medio in fluctu
quem vidimus ipsi&lt;br /&gt; submersum; dictis respondent cetera matris.'
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Brave Achetes, and our forefather Aeneas, their spirits raised
&lt;br /&gt;by these words, had been burning to break free of the mist.
&lt;br /&gt;Achates was first to speak, saying to Aeneas: ‘Son of the goddess,
&lt;br /&gt;what intention springs to your mind? You see all’s safe,
&lt;br /&gt;the fleet and our friends have been restored to us.
&lt;br /&gt;Only one is missing, whom we saw plunged in the waves:
&lt;br /&gt;all else is in accord with your mother’s words.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Vix ea fatus erat, cum circumfusa repente&lt;br /&gt; scindit se nubes
et in aethera purgat apertum.&lt;br /&gt; Restitit Aeneas claraque in luce
refulsit,
&lt;br /&gt; os umerosque deo similis; namque ipsa decoram&lt;br /&gt; caesariem
nato genetrix lumenque iuventae&lt;br /&gt; purpureum et laetos oculis
adflarat honores:
&lt;br /&gt; quale manus addunt ebori decus, aut ubi flavo&lt;br /&gt; argentum
Pariusve lapis circumdatur auro.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;He’d scarcely spoken when the mist surrounding them
&lt;br /&gt;suddenly parted, and vanished in the clear air.
&lt;br /&gt;Aeneas stood there, shining in the bright daylight,
&lt;br /&gt;like a god in shoulders and face: since his mother
&lt;br /&gt;had herself imparted to her son beauty to his hair,
&lt;br /&gt;a glow of youth, and a joyful charm to his eyes:
&lt;br /&gt;like the glory art can give to ivory, or as when silver,
&lt;br /&gt;or Parian marble, is surrounded by gold.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Tum sic reginam adloquitur, cunctisque repente&lt;br /&gt; improvisus ait:
'Coram, quem quaeritis, adsum,&lt;br /&gt; Troius Aeneas, Libycis ereptus
ab undis.&lt;br /&gt; O sola infandos Troiae miserata labores,&lt;br /&gt; quae
nos, reliquias Danaum, terraeque marisque&lt;br /&gt; omnibus exhaustos
iam casibus, omnium egenos,&lt;br /&gt; urbe, domo, socias, grates persolvere
dignas
&lt;br /&gt; non opis est nostrae, Dido, nec quicquid ubique est&lt;br /&gt; gentis
Dardaniae, magnum quae sparsa per orbem.&lt;br /&gt; Di tibi, si qua pios
respectant numina, si quid&lt;br /&gt; usquam iustitia est et mens sibi
conscia recti,&lt;br /&gt; praemia digna ferant. Quae te tam laeta tulerunt&lt;br /&gt;                saecula? Qui tanti talem genuere parentes?&lt;br /&gt; In freta dum fluvii
current, dum montibus umbrae&lt;br /&gt; lustrabunt convexa, polus dum
sidera pascet,&lt;br /&gt; semper honos nomenque tuum laudesque manebunt,&lt;br /&gt;                quae me cumque vocant terrae.' Sic fatus, amicum
&lt;br /&gt; Ilionea petit dextra, laevaque Serestum,&lt;br /&gt; post alios, fortemque
Gyan fortemque Cloanthum.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Then he addressed the queen, suddenly, surprising them all,
&lt;br /&gt;saying: ‘I am here in person, Aeneas the Trojan,
&lt;br /&gt;him whom you seek, saved from the Libyan waves.
&lt;br /&gt;O Dido, it is not in our power, nor those of our Trojan race,
&lt;br /&gt;wherever they may be, scattered through the wide world,
&lt;br /&gt;to pay you sufficient thanks, you who alone have pitied
&lt;br /&gt;Troy’s unspeakable miseries, and share your city and home
&lt;br /&gt;with us, the remnant left by the Greeks, wearied
&lt;br /&gt;by every mischance, on land and sea, and lacking everything.
&lt;br /&gt;May the gods, and the mind itself conscious of right,
&lt;br /&gt;bring you a just reward, if the gods respect the virtuous,
&lt;br /&gt;if there is justice anywhere. What happy age gave birth
&lt;br /&gt;to you? What parents produced such a child?
&lt;br /&gt;Your honour, name and praise will endure forever,
&lt;br /&gt;whatever lands may summon me, while rivers run
&lt;br /&gt;to the sea, while shadows cross mountain slopes,
&lt;br /&gt;while the sky nourishes the stars.’ So saying he grasps
&lt;br /&gt;his friend Iloneus by the right hand, Serestus with the left,
&lt;br /&gt;then others, brave Gyus and brave Cloanthus.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Obstipuit primo aspectu Sidonia Dido,&lt;br /&gt; casu deinde viri tanto,
et sic ore locuta est:&lt;br /&gt; 'Quis te, nate dea, per tanta pericula
casus
&lt;br /&gt; insequitur? Quae vis immanibus applicat oris?
&lt;br /&gt; Tune ille Aeneas, quem Dardanio Anchisae&lt;br /&gt; alma Venus Phrygii
genuit Simoentis ad undam?&lt;br /&gt; Atque equidem Teucrum memini Sidona
venire
&lt;br /&gt; finibus expulsum patriis, nova regna petentem&lt;br /&gt; auxilio
Beli; genitor tum Belus opimam&lt;br /&gt; vastabat Cyprum, et victor dicione
tenebat.
&lt;br /&gt; Tempore iam ex illo casus mihi cognitus urbis
&lt;br /&gt; Troianae nomenque tuum regesque Pelasgi.&lt;br /&gt; Ipse hostis Teucros
insigni laude ferebat,&lt;br /&gt; seque ortum antiqua Teucrorum ab stirpe
volebat.
&lt;br /&gt; Quare agite, O tectis, iuvenes, succedite nostris.
&lt;br /&gt; Me quoque per multos similis fortuna labores&lt;br /&gt; iactatam
hac demum voluit consistere terra.&lt;br /&gt; Non ignara mali, miseris
succurrere disco.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Sidonian Dido was first amazed at the hero’s looks
&lt;br /&gt;then at his great misfortunes, and she spoke, saying:
&lt;br /&gt;‘Son of a goddess, what fate pursues you through all
&lt;br /&gt;these dangers? What force drives you to these barbarous shores?
&lt;br /&gt;Are you truly that Aeneas whom kindly Venus bore
&lt;br /&gt;to Trojan Anchises, by the waters of Phrygian Simois?
&lt;br /&gt;Indeed, I myself remember Teucer coming to Sidon,
&lt;br /&gt;exiled from his country’s borders, seeking a new kingdom
&lt;br /&gt;with Belus’s help: Belus, my father, was laying waste
&lt;br /&gt;rich Cyprus, and, as victor, held it by his authority.
&lt;br /&gt;Since then the fall of the Trojan city is known to me,
&lt;br /&gt;and your name, and those of the Greek kings.
&lt;br /&gt;Even their enemy granted the Teucrians high praise,
&lt;br /&gt;maintaining they were born of the ancient Teucrian stock.
&lt;br /&gt;So come, young lords, and enter our palace.
&lt;br /&gt;Fortune, pursuing me too, through many similar troubles,
&lt;br /&gt;willed that I would find peace at last in this land.
&lt;br /&gt;Not being unknown to evil, I’ve learned to aid the unhappy.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Sic memorat; simul Aenean in regia ducit&lt;br /&gt; tecta, simul divom
templis indicit honorem.&lt;br /&gt; Nec minus interea sociis ad litora
mittit
&lt;br /&gt; viginti tauros, magnorum horrentia centum&lt;br /&gt; terga suum,
pinguis centum cum matribus agnos,&lt;br /&gt; munera laetitiamque dii.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;So she speaks, and leads Aeneas into the royal house,
&lt;br /&gt;and proclaims, as well, offerings at the god’s temples.
&lt;br /&gt;She sends no less than twenty bulls to his friends
&lt;br /&gt;on the shore, and a hundred of her largest pigs with
&lt;br /&gt;bristling backs, a hundred fat lambs with the ewes,
&lt;br /&gt;and joyful gifts of wine,
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;At domus interior regali splendida luxu&lt;br /&gt; instruitur, mediisque
parant convivia tectis:&lt;br /&gt; arte laboratae vestes ostroque superbo,
&lt;br /&gt; ingens argentum mensis, caelataque in auro&lt;br /&gt; fortia facta
patrum, series longissima rerum&lt;br /&gt; per tot ducta viros antiqua
ab origine gentis.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;but the interior of the palace
&lt;br /&gt;is laid out with royal luxury, and they prepare
&lt;br /&gt;a feast in the centre of the palace: covers worked
&lt;br /&gt;skilfully in princely purple, massive silverware
&lt;br /&gt;on the tables, and her forefathers’ heroic deeds
&lt;br /&gt;engraved in gold, a long series of exploits traced
&lt;br /&gt;through many heroes, since the ancient origins of her people.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Aeneas (neque enim patrius consistere mentem&lt;br /&gt; passus amor) rapidum
ad navis praemittit Achaten,&lt;br /&gt; Ascanio ferat haec, ipsumque ad
moenia ducat;&lt;br /&gt; omnis in Ascanio cari stat cura parentis.&lt;br /&gt;                Munera praeterea, Iliacis erepta ruinis,&lt;br /&gt; ferre iubet, pallam
signis auroque rigentem,&lt;br /&gt; et circumtextum croceo velamen acantho,&lt;br /&gt;                ornatus Argivae Helenae, quos illa Mycenis,&lt;br /&gt; Pergama cum peteret
inconcessosque hymenaeos,&lt;br /&gt; extulerat, matris Ledae mirabile
donum:
&lt;br /&gt; praeterea sceptrum, Ilione quod gesserat olim,&lt;br /&gt; maxima
natarum Priami, colloque monile&lt;br /&gt; bacatum, et duplicem gemmis
auroque coronam.&lt;br /&gt; Haec celerans ita ad naves tendebat Achates.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Aeneas quickly sends Achates to the ships
&lt;br /&gt;to carry the news to Ascanius (since a father’s love
&lt;br /&gt;won’t let his mind rest) and bring him to the city:
&lt;br /&gt;on Ascanius all the care of a fond parent is fixed.
&lt;br /&gt;He commands him to bring gifts too, snatched
&lt;br /&gt;from the ruins of Troy, a figured robe stiff with gold,
&lt;br /&gt;and a cloak fringed with yellow acanthus,
&lt;br /&gt;worn by Helen of Argos, brought from Mycenae
&lt;br /&gt;when she sailed to Troy and her unlawful marriage,
&lt;br /&gt;a wonderful gift from her mother Leda:
&lt;br /&gt;and the sceptre that Ilione, Priam’s eldest daughter,
&lt;br /&gt;once carried, and a necklace of pearls, and a double-coronet
&lt;br /&gt;of jewels and gold. Achates, hastening to fulfil
&lt;br /&gt;these commands, took his way towards the ships.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;At Cytherea novas artes, nova pectore versat&lt;br /&gt; Consilia,
ut faciem mutatus et ora Cupido&lt;br /&gt; pro dulci Ascanio veniat, donisque
furentem
&lt;br /&gt; incendat reginam, atque ossibus implicet ignem;&lt;br /&gt; quippe
domum timet ambiguam Tyriosque bilinguis;&lt;br /&gt; urit atrox Iuno,
et sub noctem cura recursat.&lt;br /&gt; Ergo his aligerum dictis adfatur
Amorem:
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;But Venus was planning new wiles and stratagems
&lt;br /&gt;in her heart: how Cupid, altered in looks, might arrive
&lt;br /&gt;in place of sweet Ascanius, and arouse the passionate queen
&lt;br /&gt;by his gifts, and entwine the fire in her bones: truly she
fears
&lt;br /&gt;the unreliability of this house, and the duplicitous Tyrians:
&lt;br /&gt;unyielding Juno angers her, and her worries increase with nightfall.
&lt;br /&gt;So she speaks these words to winged Cupid:
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;'Nate, meae vires, mea magna potentia solus,&lt;br /&gt; nate, patris summi
qui tela Typhoia temnis,&lt;br /&gt; ad te confugio et supplex tua numina
posco.
&lt;br /&gt; Frater ut Aeneas pelago tuus omnia circum&lt;br /&gt; litora iactetur
odiis Iunonis iniquae,&lt;br /&gt; nota tibi, et nostro doluisti saepe
dolore.
&lt;br /&gt; Hunc Phoenissa tenet Dido blandisque moratur
&lt;br /&gt; vocibus; et vereor, quo se Iunonia vertant&lt;br /&gt; hospitia; haud
tanto cessabit cardine rerum.&lt;br /&gt; Quocirca capere ante dolis et
cingere flamma&lt;br /&gt; reginam meditor, ne quo se numine mutet,&lt;br /&gt;                sed magno Aeneae mecum teneatur amore.&lt;br /&gt; Qua facere id possis,
nostram nunc accipe mentem.&lt;br /&gt; Regius accitu cari genitoris ad
urbem
&lt;br /&gt; Sidoniam puer ire parat, mea maxima cura,&lt;br /&gt; dona ferens,
pelago et flammis restantia Troiae:&lt;br /&gt; hunc ego sopitum somno
super alta Cythera&lt;br /&gt; aut super Idalium sacrata sede recondam,&lt;br /&gt;                ne qua scire dolos mediusve occurrere possit.&lt;br /&gt; Tu faciem illius
noctem non amplius unam&lt;br /&gt; falle dolo, et notos pueri puer indue
voltus,
&lt;br /&gt; ut, cum te gremio accipiet laetissima Dido&lt;br /&gt; regalis inter
mensas laticemque Lyaeum,&lt;br /&gt; cum dabit amplexus atque oscula dulcia
figet,
&lt;br /&gt; occultum inspires ignem fallasque veneno.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;‘My son, you who alone are my great strength, my power,
&lt;br /&gt;a son who scorns mighty Jupiter’s Typhoean thunderbolts,
&lt;br /&gt;I ask your help, and humbly call on your divine will.
&lt;br /&gt;It’s known to you how Aeneas, your brother, is driven
&lt;br /&gt;over the sea, round all the shores, by bitter Juno’s hatred,
&lt;br /&gt;and you have often grieved with my grief.
&lt;br /&gt;Phoenician Dido holds him there, delaying him with flattery,
&lt;br /&gt;and I fear what may come of Juno’s hospitality:
&lt;br /&gt;at such a critical turn of events she’ll not be idle.
&lt;br /&gt;So I intend to deceive the queen with guile, and encircle
&lt;br /&gt;her with passion, so that no divine will can rescue her,
&lt;br /&gt;but she’ll be seized, with me, by deep love for Aeneas.
&lt;br /&gt;Now listen to my thoughts on how you can achieve this.
&lt;br /&gt;Summoned by his dear father, the royal child,
&lt;br /&gt;my greatest concern, prepares to go to the Sidonian city,
&lt;br /&gt;carrying gifts that survived the sea, and the flames of Troy.
&lt;br /&gt;I’ll lull him to sleep and hide him in my sacred shrine
&lt;br /&gt;on the heights of Cythera or Idalium, so he can know
&lt;br /&gt;nothing of my deceptions, or interrupt them mid-way.
&lt;br /&gt;For no more than a single night imitate his looks by art,
&lt;br /&gt;and, a boy yourself, take on the known face of a boy,
&lt;br /&gt;so that when Dido takes you to her breast, joyfully,
&lt;br /&gt;amongst the royal feast, and the flowing wine,
&lt;br /&gt;when she embraces you, and plants sweet kisses on you,
&lt;br /&gt;you’ll breathe hidden fire into her, deceive her with your
poison.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Paret Amor dictis carae genetricis, et alas&lt;br /&gt; exuit, et gressu
gaudens incedit Iuli.&lt;br /&gt; At Venus Ascanio placidam per membra
quietem
&lt;br /&gt; inrigat, et fotum gremio dea tollit in altos&lt;br /&gt; Idaliae lucos,
ubi mollis amaracus illum&lt;br /&gt; floribus et dulci adspirans complectitur
umbra.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Cupid obeys his dear mother’s words, sets aside his wings,
&lt;br /&gt;and laughingly trips along with Iulus’s step.
&lt;br /&gt;But Venus pours gentle sleep over Ascanius’s limbs,
&lt;br /&gt;and warming him in her breast, carries him, with divine power,
&lt;br /&gt;to Idalia’s high groves, where soft marjoram smothers him
&lt;br /&gt;in flowers, and the breath of its sweet shade.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Iamque ibat dicto parens et dona Cupido&lt;br /&gt; regia portabat Tyriis,
duce laetus Achate.&lt;br /&gt; Cum venit, aulaeis iam se regina superbis
&lt;br /&gt; aurea composuit sponda mediamque locavit.&lt;br /&gt; Iam pater Aeneas
et iam Troiana iuventus&lt;br /&gt; conveniunt, stratoque super discumbitur
ostro.
&lt;br /&gt; Dant famuli manibus lymphas, Cereremque canistris
&lt;br /&gt; expediunt, tonsisque ferunt mantelia villis.&lt;br /&gt; Quinquaginta
intus famulae, quibus ordine longam&lt;br /&gt; cura penum struere, et
flammis adolere Penatis;&lt;br /&gt; centum aliae totidemque pares aetate
ministri,
&lt;br /&gt; qui dapibus mensas onerent et pocula ponant.
&lt;br /&gt; Nec non et Tyrii per limina laeta frequentes&lt;br /&gt; convenere,
toris iussi discumbere pictis.&lt;br /&gt; Mirantur dona Aeneae, mirantur
Iulum
&lt;br /&gt; flagrantisque dei voltus simulataque verba,&lt;br /&gt; [pallamque
et pictum croceo velamen acantho.]&lt;br /&gt; Praecipue infelix, pesti
devota futurae,&lt;br /&gt; expleri mentem nequit ardescitque tuendo&lt;br /&gt;                Phoenissa, et pariter puero donisque movetur.&lt;br /&gt; Ille ubi complexu
Aeneae colloque pependit&lt;br /&gt; et magnum falsi implevit genitoris
amorem,
&lt;br /&gt; reginam petit haec oculis, haec pectore toto&lt;br /&gt; haeret et
interdum gremio fovet, inscia Dido,&lt;br /&gt; insidat quantus miserae
deus; at memor ille&lt;br /&gt; matris Acidaliae paulatim abolere Sychaeum&lt;br /&gt;                incipit, et vivo temptat praevertere amore&lt;br /&gt; iam pridem resides
animos desuetaque corda.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Now, obedient to her orders, delighting in Achetes as guide,
&lt;br /&gt;Cupid goes off carrying royal gifts for the Tyrians.
&lt;br /&gt;When he arrives the queen has already settled herself
&lt;br /&gt;in the centre, on her golden couch under royal canopies.
&lt;br /&gt;Now our forefather Aeneas and the youth of Troy
&lt;br /&gt;gather there, and recline on cloths of purple.
&lt;br /&gt;Servants pour water over their hands: serve bread
&lt;br /&gt;from baskets: and bring napkins of smooth cloth.
&lt;br /&gt;Inside there are fifty female servants, in a long line,
&lt;br /&gt;whose task it is to prepare the meal, and tend the hearth fires:
&lt;br /&gt;a hundred more, and as many pages of like age,
&lt;br /&gt;to load the tables with food, and fill the cups.
&lt;br /&gt;And the Tyrians too are gathered in crowds through the festive
&lt;br /&gt;halls, summoned to recline on the embroidered couches.
&lt;br /&gt;They marvel at Aeneas’s gifts, marvel at Iulus,
&lt;br /&gt;the god’s brilliant appearance, and deceptive words,
&lt;br /&gt;at the robe, and the cloak embroidered with yellow acanthus.
&lt;br /&gt;The unfortunate Phoenician above all, doomed to future ruin,
&lt;br /&gt;cannot pacify her feelings, and catches fire with gazing,
&lt;br /&gt;stirred equally by the child and by the gifts.
&lt;br /&gt;He, having hung in an embrace round Aeneas’s neck,
&lt;br /&gt;and sated the deceived father’s great love,
&lt;br /&gt;seeks out the queen. Dido, clings to him with her eyes
&lt;br /&gt;and with her heart, taking him now and then on her lap,
&lt;br /&gt;unaware how great a god is entering her, to her sorrow.
&lt;br /&gt;But he, remembering his Cyprian mother’s wishes,
&lt;br /&gt;begins gradually to erase all thought of Sychaeus,
&lt;br /&gt;and works at seducing her mind, so long unstirred,
&lt;br /&gt;and her heart unused to love, with living passion.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col latin&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Postquam prima quies epulis, mensaeque remotae,&lt;br /&gt; crateras magnos
statuunt et vina coronant.&lt;br /&gt; Fit strepitus tectis, vocemque per
ampla volutant&lt;br /&gt; atria; dependent lychni laquearibus aureis&lt;br /&gt;                incensi, et noctem flammis funalia vincunt.&lt;br /&gt; Hic regina gravem
gemmis auroque poposcit&lt;br /&gt; implevitque mero pateram, quam Belus
et omnes&lt;br /&gt; a Belo soliti; tum facta silentia tectis:&lt;br /&gt; 'Iuppiter,
hospitibus nam te dare iura loquuntur,&lt;br /&gt; hunc laetum Tyriisque
diem Troiaque profectis&lt;br /&gt; esse velis, nostrosque huius meminisse
minores.
&lt;br /&gt; Adsit laetitiae Bacchus dator, et bona Iuno;&lt;br /&gt; et vos, O,
coetum, Tyrii, celebrate faventes.'&lt;br /&gt; Dixit, et in mensam laticum
libavit honorem,&lt;br /&gt; primaque, libato, summo tenus attigit ore,
&lt;br /&gt; tum Bitiae dedit increpitans; ille impiger hausit&lt;br /&gt; spumantem
pateram, et pleno se proluit auro&lt;br /&gt; post alii proceres. Cithara
crinitus Iopas&lt;br /&gt; personat aurata, docuit quem maximus Atlas.
&lt;br /&gt; Hic canit errantem lunam solisque labores;&lt;br /&gt; unde hominum
genus et pecudes; unde imber et ignes;&lt;br /&gt; Arcturum pluviasque
Hyadas geminosque Triones;&lt;br /&gt; quid tantum Oceano properent se
tinguere soles&lt;br /&gt; hiberni, vel quae tardis mora noctibus obstet.&lt;br /&gt;                Ingeminant plausu Tyrii, Troesque sequuntur.&lt;br /&gt; Nec non et vario
noctem sermone trahebat&lt;br /&gt; infelix Dido, longumque bibebat amorem,&lt;br /&gt;                multa super Priamo rogitans, super Hectore multa;&lt;br /&gt; nunc quibus
Aurorae venisset filius armis,&lt;br /&gt; nunc quales Diomedis equi, nunc
quantus Achilles.&lt;br /&gt; 'Immo age, et a prima dic, hospes, origine
nobis
&lt;br /&gt; insidias,' inquit, 'Danaum, casusque tuorum,&lt;br /&gt; erroresque
tuos; nam te iam septima portat&lt;br /&gt; omnibus errantem terris et
fluctibus aestas.'
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col english&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;At the first lull in the feasting, the tables were cleared,
&lt;br /&gt;and they set out vast bowls, and wreathed the wine with garlands.
&lt;br /&gt;Noise filled the palace, and voices rolled out across the wide
halls:
&lt;br /&gt;bright lamps hung from the golden ceilings,
&lt;br /&gt;and blazing candles dispelled the night.
&lt;br /&gt;Then the queen asked for a drinking-cup, heavy
&lt;br /&gt;with gold and jewels, that Belus and all Belus’s line
&lt;br /&gt;were accustomed to use, and filled it
&lt;br /&gt;with wine. Then the halls were silent. She spoke:
&lt;br /&gt;‘Jupiter, since they say you’re the one who creates
&lt;br /&gt;the laws of hospitality, let this be a happy day
&lt;br /&gt;for the Tyrians and those from Troy,
&lt;br /&gt;and let it be remembered by our children.
&lt;br /&gt;Let Bacchus, the joy-bringer, and kind Juno be present,
&lt;br /&gt;and you, O Phoenicians, make this gathering festive.’
&lt;br /&gt;She spoke and poured an offering of wine onto the table,
&lt;br /&gt;and after the libation was the first to touch the bowl to her
lips,
&lt;br /&gt;then she gave it to Bitias, challenging him: he briskly drained
&lt;br /&gt;the brimming cup, drenching himself in its golden fullness,
&lt;br /&gt;then other princes drank. Iolas, the long-haired, made
&lt;br /&gt;his golden lyre resound, he whom great Atlas taught.
&lt;br /&gt;He sang of the wandering moon and the sun’s labours,
&lt;br /&gt;where men and beasts came from, and rain and fire,
&lt;br /&gt;of Arcturus, the rainy Hyades, the two Bears:
&lt;br /&gt;why the winter suns rush to dip themselves in the sea,
&lt;br /&gt;and what delay makes the slow nights linger.
&lt;br /&gt;The Tyrians redoubled their applause, the Trojans too.
&lt;br /&gt;And unfortunate Dido, she too spent the night
&lt;br /&gt;in conversation, and drank deep of her passion,
&lt;br /&gt;asking endlessly about Priam and Hector:
&lt;br /&gt;now about the armour that Memnon, son of the Dawn,
&lt;br /&gt;came with to Troy, what kind were Diomed’s horses,
&lt;br /&gt;how great was Achilles. ‘But come, my guest, tell us
&lt;br /&gt;from the start all the Greek trickery, your men’s mishaps,
&lt;br /&gt;and your wanderings: since it’s the seventh summer now
&lt;br /&gt;that brings you here, in your journey, over every land and
sea.’
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fixed-bottom&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;collapseExample&quot; class=&quot;container collapse&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col col-11&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;dictionary&quot; src=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Aeneas#Latin&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; height:300px;margin:0px;border:0px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col col-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-danger&quot; data-toggle=&quot;collapse&quot; href=&quot;#collapseExample&quot; aria-expanded=&quot;false&quot; aria-controls=&quot;collapseExample&quot;&gt;
x
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
function sanitized(word)
{
// https://stackoverflow.com/questions/4328500/how-can-i-strip-all-punctuation-from-a-string-in-javascript-using-regex
const punctuationless = word.replace(
/[.,\/#!$%\^&amp;\*;:{}=\-_`~()]/g, &quot;&quot;);
// https://stackoverflow.com/questions/863800/replacing-diacritics-in-javascript
return punctuationless.normalize('NFKD').replace(
/[^\w\s.-_\/]/g,
'');
}

function lookup(word)
{
console.log(&quot;looking up &quot; + word);
document.getElementById(&quot;dictionary&quot;).src =
&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/&quot; + sanitized(
word) +
&quot;#Latin&quot;;
$('#collapseExample').collapse('show');
}

function createLookup(text)
{
return text.replace(
/([a-zA-Z\u00C0-\u017F]+)(?!\w*&gt;)/g,
'&lt;span onclick=\'lookup(&quot;$1&quot;)\'&gt;$1&lt;/span&gt;');
}


var latinElements =
document.getElementsByClassName(&quot;latin&quot;);
for (var i = 0; i &lt; latinElements.length; ++i)
{
latinElements[i].innerHTML = createLookup(latinElements[i].innerHTML);
}


&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Translated by A. S. Kline. Formatting in progress.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exponential Dynamic Programming</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/12/27/expdp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exponential Dynamic Programming" /><published>2017-12-28T04:50:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-12-28T04:50:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/12/27/expdp</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/12/27/expdp/">&lt;p&gt;Dynamic programming can turn exponential solutions into polynomial solutions,
but it can also help turn factorial solutions into exponential. Problems where
the bound on $n$ is 20, for example, signal that an exponential solution is the
one required. Consider &lt;a href=&quot;http://usaco.org/index.php?page=viewproblem2&amp;amp;cpid=494&quot;&gt;the following
problem&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Problem 1: Guard Mark [Bill Cooperman, 2014]

Farmer John and his herd are playing frisbee.  Bessie throws the
frisbee down the field, but it's going straight to Mark the field hand
on the other team!  Mark has height H (1 &amp;lt;= H &amp;lt;= 1,000,000,000), but
there are N cows on Bessie's team gathered around Mark (2 &amp;lt;= N &amp;lt;= 20).
They can only catch the frisbee if they can stack up to be at least as
high as Mark.  Each of the N cows has a height, weight, and strength.
A cow's strength indicates the maximum amount of total weight of the
cows that can be stacked above her.  

Given these constraints, Bessie wants to know if it is possible for
her team to build a tall enough stack to catch the frisbee, and if so,
what is the maximum safety factor of such a stack.  The safety factor
of a stack is the amount of weight that can be added to the top of the
stack without exceeding any cow's strength.

INPUT: (file guard.in)

The first line of input contains N and H.

The next N lines of input each describe a cow, giving its height,
weight, and strength.  All are positive integers at most 1 billion.

SAMPLE INPUT:

4 10
9 4 1
3 3 5
5 5 10
4 4 5

OUTPUT: (file guard.out)

If Bessie's team can build a stack tall enough to catch the frisbee,
please output the maximum achievable safety factor for such a stack.
Otherwise output &quot;Mark is too tall&quot; (without the quotes).

SAMPLE OUTPUT:

2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can try the $O(N!)$ brute force, trying every permutation of cows possible.
However, this is far too slow. $N \le 20$ hints at an exponential solution, so
we think of trying every possible subset of the cows. Given a subset $S$ of
cows, the height reached is the same, so perhaps we sort the subset by
strength, and put the strongest cow on the bottom. We see that this greedy
approach fails: suppose that the first cow has weight 1 and strength 3 and the
second cow has weight 4 and strength 2. Greedy would tell us to put the first
cow on the bottom, but this fails, while putting the second cow on the bottom
succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When greedy fails, the next strategy we look at is dynamic programming. To
decide whether $S$ is stable, we have to find whether there exists a cow $j$ in
$S$ that can support the weight of all the other cows in $S$. But how do we
know whether the set $S \setminus {j}$ is stable? This is where dynamic
programming comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to a $O(N 2^N)$ solution. This seems like a pain to code
iteratively, but there is a nice fact about subsets: there is a cute bijection
from the subsets of ${0,1,2, \ldots, N-1}$ to the integers from 0 to $2^N -
1$. That is, the subset ${0,2,5,7}$ maps to $2^0 + 2^2 + 2^5 + 2^7 = 165$ in
the bijection. We call this technique &lt;em&gt;masking&lt;/em&gt;. We require all the
subsets of $S$ to be processed before $S$ is processed, but that property is
also handled by our bijection, since subtracting a power of 2 from a number
decreases it. With a little knowledge of bit operators, this can be handled
easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;fstream&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;algorithm&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;climits&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;safety_factor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;strength&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifstream&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;guard.in&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ofstream&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;guard.out&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;strength&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ans&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;safety_factor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;INT_MAX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// index represents S
&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// index &amp;amp; (1 &amp;lt;&amp;lt; j) is nonzero when j is in S
&lt;/span&gt;                &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; 
                        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;strength&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; 
                            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;safety_factor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;safety_factor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; 
                            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;min&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;strength&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_weight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; 
                            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;safety_factor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]));&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total_height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ans&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ans&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;safety_factor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ans&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Mark is too tall&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;endl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ans&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;endl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;close&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;close&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; is the bitwise and function, while &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt; is the left shift operator.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dynamic programming can turn exponential solutions into polynomial solutions, but it can also help turn factorial solutions into exponential. Problems where the bound on $n$ is 20, for example, signal that an exponential solution is the one required. Consider the following problem:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zhuangzi, Catan, and Classes</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/11/22/zhuangzi-catan-classes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zhuangzi, Catan, and Classes" /><published>2017-11-22T22:30:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-11-22T22:30:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/11/22/zhuangzi-catan-classes</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/11/22/zhuangzi-catan-classes/">&lt;p&gt;Thanksgiving provides me with some well-needed rest before I jump back in to
finish the semester, giving me time to reflect a little bit and collect some
random thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zhuangzi's passage on the happiness of fish discusses the relativity of
knowledge: How does Zhuangzi know whether the fish are happy? But Huizi cannot
know what Zhuangzi knows… the cycle continues. Zhuangzi finishes with a play
on the word 安, which can mean either &quot;how&quot; or &quot;where.&quot; Last night, I read a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://paper-republic.org/lucasklein/anarchist-anthropology-happy-fish-and-translation/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; 
that focused on that last line, and I found both the post and its comment chain
enjoyable to peruse, comparing relativity of perspective to relativity of
location (hence 安 as &quot;whence&quot;) and the joy of philosophy to the playfulness of
fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks ago, a game of Catan ended in an interesting way: it was Will's
turn, and should Will end his turn it would be mine, and I would immediately
build a settlement with the resources in my hand and win the game. Andrew,
who almost has the resources to win himself, recognized that if he gave all of
his resources to Will, he could enable Will to win before me. Wishing to
prolong the game, he threatened to do so unless I forfeited the resources in my
hand that would have allowed me to win. I gave up my resources and was forced
to roll on my turn; I still got lucky with my roll, but I wonder if Andrew
could have strong-armed me further than he had done. Perhaps the game could
have been prolonged further if Andrew, Will, and I had entered an agreement to
give all of our resources to Rowen, who was far away in last place. My game of
Catan presented a similar situation to Risk, in which a player might threaten
to retaliate in full force against any invader, essentially sacking the current
game to win the metagame. This also leads me to wonder how much negative
expected value I would be willing to take on to prevent my opponents from
winning high positive expected value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classes are finally coming to a close. All classes build up in nature; the end
material rests on the foundation laid in the beginning. Yet I think I stand
more to learn at the end of this semester than at the end of my previous
semesters: Math 114 is entering Fourier analysis and exploring some familiar
results from complex analysis, like the mean-value property of harmonic
functions, in a real analysis context (perhaps its original context); Stat 210
is covering the Central Limit Theorem in more rigor; ER 18 is synthesizing all
of the thinkers we'd covered in the class; USW 35 is now proposing and
discussing solutions to the problems in our education system. Everything is
coming together, but it's difficult to keep track of everything, and truly,
&lt;em&gt;tempus fugit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Thanksgiving provides me with some well-needed rest before I jump back in to finish the semester, giving me time to reflect a little bit and collect some random thoughts.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">sicut cor ita cervus</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/10/30/cervus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sicut cor ita cervus" /><published>2017-10-31T06:30:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-10-31T06:30:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/10/30/cervus</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/10/30/cervus/">&lt;p&gt;I knew I belonged in Harvard Glee Club when we sang a TTBB arrangement of
Palestrina's &lt;em&gt;Sicut cervus&lt;/em&gt; at the first rehearsal freshman year. The text is
an adaptation of Psalm 42:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Sicut cervus desiderat ad fontes aquarum, ita
desiderat anima mea ad te, Deus&lt;/em&gt;. The sheet music we were using had a typo in
the English translation, using &lt;em&gt;heart&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;hart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as the translation
for &lt;em&gt;cervus&lt;/em&gt;. Interestingly, just as &lt;em&gt;hart&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;heart&lt;/em&gt; sound similar, so do
&lt;em&gt;cervus&lt;/em&gt; and the Latin word for &lt;em&gt;heart&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;cor&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and even more
interestingly, this is not a coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two words in each language sound similar because they are derived from
words that sound similar in Proto-Indo-European. &lt;em&gt;Heart&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cor&lt;/em&gt; are derived
from PIE &lt;em&gt;*ḱḗr&lt;/em&gt; (oblique stem &lt;em&gt;*ḱr̥d-&lt;/em&gt;), which is well-attested across the many
branches of Indo-European; another familiar example is Greek &lt;em&gt;kardiá&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The
relationship between &lt;em&gt;heart&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cor&lt;/em&gt; is unexceptional to anyone with exposure
to PIE. Less commonly known is the corresponding relationship between &lt;em&gt;hart&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;cervus&lt;/em&gt;, both rarer words in their respective languages. &lt;em&gt;Hart&lt;/em&gt; is derived
from PIE &lt;em&gt;*ḱerh₂-&lt;/em&gt; (&quot;horn&quot;),&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which is also the source of &lt;em&gt;cervus&lt;/em&gt;.  We see
that &lt;em&gt;*ḱḗr&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;*ḱerh₂-&lt;/em&gt; sound similar, and by regularity of sound change,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
words derived from similar-sounding roots in the proto-language will continue
to sound similar in daughter languages, which resulted in the confusion in the
English translation of &lt;em&gt;Sicut cervus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Psalm 41:2 in the Vulgate. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;hart &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;. An adult male deer, especially a red deer over five years old. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/hart&quot;&gt;Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;cor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;cordis&lt;/em&gt;. From which we derive the words &lt;em&gt;core&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;accord&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;cordial&lt;/em&gt;, etc. via French. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;καρδιά&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;kardiá&lt;/em&gt;). From which we derive the root &lt;em&gt;cardio-&lt;/em&gt; and therefore words like &lt;em&gt;cardiology&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cardiovascular&lt;/em&gt;, and other words like &lt;em&gt;tachycardia&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*ḱerh₂-&lt;/em&gt; (&quot;horn&quot;). From which we also derive the English words &lt;em&gt;horn&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;flugelhorn&lt;/em&gt; from German; &lt;em&gt;cornucopia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;cornea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;cervix&lt;/em&gt; from Latin and &lt;em&gt;unicorn&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;carrot&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;cerebral&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;corner&lt;/em&gt; from Latin via French; &lt;em&gt;keratin&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;rhinoceros&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;triceratops&lt;/em&gt; from Greek and &lt;em&gt;cranium&lt;/em&gt; from Greek via Latin.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/*ker-&quot;&gt;Online Etymology Dictionary&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The notable sound changes here are PIE &lt;em&gt;*ḱ&lt;/em&gt; resulting in English &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; and Latin &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;, often spelled &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;, which later palatalized before the front vowels &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;. Another sound change is PIE &lt;em&gt;*d&lt;/em&gt; resulting in English &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; and Latin &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I knew I belonged in Harvard Glee Club when we sang a TTBB arrangement of Palestrina's Sicut cervus at the first rehearsal freshman year. The text is an adaptation of Psalm 42:1 Sicut cervus desiderat ad fontes aquarum, ita desiderat anima mea ad te, Deus. The sheet music we were using had a typo in the English translation, using heart instead of hart2 as the translation for cervus. Interestingly, just as hart and heart sound similar, so do cervus and the Latin word for heart, cor,3 and even more interestingly, this is not a coincidence. Psalm 41:2 in the Vulgate. &amp;#8617; hart n. An adult male deer, especially a red deer over five years old. Oxford English Dictionary &amp;#8617; cor, cordis. From which we derive the words core, accord, cordial, etc. via French. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Skinny Repeal</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/27/skinny-repeal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Skinny Repeal" /><published>2017-07-28T08:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-07-28T08:00:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/27/skinny-repeal</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/27/skinny-repeal/">&lt;p&gt;Today, Republicans announced the Health Care Freedom Act, notably removing the
individual and employer mandates from the Affordable Care Act. By removing the
requirement for people to have insurance, Republicans tout this bill as
restoring choice to the American consumer, thereby reducing healthcare prices.
This sounds like music in a speech: health insurance providers still can't
discriminate against people with pre-existing conditions, but now consumers are
not forced to pay for insurance they don't want! This seems like a double-win
for the American people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's the catch: not only will a skinny repeal not lower costs, it's actually
much worse than having Obamacare repealed entirely.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
I wish I had more time to do more research and flesh out all the statistics and
details, since health care is such a crucial topic in today's age, but our
government, so insistent on pushing repeal through as a political move,
compelled a quick response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obamacare's monumental achievement was to lower healh care costs to the most
vulnerable. Some people are at greater risk of disease than others: this has
held true in the past and will continue to be true for the foreseeable future.
People with different genetics, different lifestyles, and different previous
illnesses face different likelihoods of falling ill in the future. We can get a
sense of consumer behavior through a simple model: at period 1, say one half of
the population has a 20% chance and the other half of the population has an 80%
chance of falling ill in period 2. Let's also suppose that, without insurance,
a consumer pays \$0 when healthy and \$1000 when ill in period 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pre-Obamacare, people with the highest risk faced the highest insurance
premiums, and people with the lowest risk faced the lowest. Insurance is not
inherently a transfer from the low-risk to the high-risk; it is a means for
each individual person to hedge their bets. Almost everyone is risk-averse to
some degree: given a choice between \$500 guaranteed or a 50% chance at \$1000,
I think most people would choose the guaranteed money. Insurance is precisely
this. An insurance company, by aggregating independent probabilities, can
stabilize risk for everyone. Before the Affordable Care Act, the fair insurance
rate for low-risk individuals is to pay \$200 and for high-risk individuals to
pay \$800 in period 1. Because individuals are risk-averse, both low- and
high-risk individuals are happy with this plan. By discrimination, insurance
companies can set fair prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here is that oftentimes individuals find themselves at a high risk
of disease at no fault of their own because of bad luck previously in life or
even before birth. A core idea behind Obamacare is to share health care costs
across all individuals, irrespective of high or low risk levels. Democrats
justified this with a plea for fairness: it's largely not a high-risk
individual's fault that they are more likely to fall ill. Republicans oppose
this also on the grounds of fairness: it's not the responsibility of the
low-risk individual to have to pay for the high-risk individual's bad luck,
either. My purpose here is not to convince the reader one way or another on
this issue, but merely that skinny repeal is a strictly worse option than both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-Obamacare, insurance companies can no longer discriminate on pre-existing
conditions. In our model, this means that insurance companies set a single
price for both high- and low-risk individuals. However, Obamacare also includes
an individual mandate: all individuals must buy insurance. Knowing that all
individuals must buy insurance, companies will set the fair price of \$500 for
everyone. This is a great deal for high-risk individuals, since they are now
paying much lower than they would have without Obamacare. Low-risk individuals
now must pay more than they are willing, but they must buy the insurance anyway
to subsidize the high-risk individuals' health care. Behind the veil of
ignorance, prior to knowing risk level, paying \$500 is perfectly fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble comes when we remove the individual mandate, but leave insurance
companies unable to discriminate. Let's suppose the insurance company sets its
price at \$500 as before. The high-risk individuals will all buy this plan, but
none of the low-risk individuals will buy it. In this scenario, the insurance
company will lose money, so it will certainly not set its price at \$500, or
indeed, any price less than \$800.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the price settles at \$800, high-risk individuals will pay the same amount
as without Obamacare, but low-risk individuals will be left entirely uninsured,
which is a strictly worse outcome than without Obamacare at all assuming
risk-aversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results are even worse with more complicated models than my simple
two-state, two-period example. In the real world, people have all different
probabilities of falling ill. It follows fairly easily from the simple model
that insurance companies will only charge the fair price of the individuals at
greatest risk, since at any other price, they will lose money. As we spread
more and more people across this continuum of illness risk, we see that more
and more people are left without access to insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banning price discrimination without an individual mandate, then, is
essentially a ban on health care insurance entirely. Despite making for a great
sound bite, skinny repeal is an incredibly irresponsible and damaging political
maneuver, and if it is enacted, skinny repeal is far, far worse for the
American people than full repeal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today, Republicans announced the Health Care Freedom Act, notably removing the individual and employer mandates from the Affordable Care Act. By removing the requirement for people to have insurance, Republicans tout this bill as restoring choice to the American consumer, thereby reducing healthcare prices. This sounds like music in a speech: health insurance providers still can't discriminate against people with pre-existing conditions, but now consumers are not forced to pay for insurance they don't want! This seems like a double-win for the American people. Here's the catch: not only will a skinny repeal not lower costs, it's actually much worse than having Obamacare repealed entirely.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">End-of-Life Agency</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/26/eol-agency/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="End-of-Life Agency" /><published>2017-07-27T07:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T07:00:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/26/eol-agency</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/26/eol-agency/">&lt;p&gt;To what extent should people be able to control their futures, and to what
extent can the government take that away? Last week, Jacob and I were
discussing whether the government has done too little or too much in shaping
our life decisions. The United States gives its citizens plenty of agency in
weighing the short and long term. I can choose what food I eat and how much I
exercise, as it's entirely my decision whether having a satisfying but
unhealthy lifestyle is worth shaving years off the end of my life. I assess
risk constantly, from inching closer to the edge of a cliff for that perfect
photo to simply biking to and from work, internalizing the probability that I
get into an accident. I can choose my career: some jobs are more financially
risky while some are physically more dangerous, some better fit my skill set
while others I find more intrinsically appealling, but the government leaves
all of these factors up to the market to set prices and wages, and from there I
make my own choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in plenty of other instances, we don't get too much say in our future.
Although I make the decision to hit the road, once I do, I must wear a seat
belt. The government compels us into Social Security, essentially forcing us to
prepare for retirement.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Suicide is perhaps the most extreme expression of
determining one's fate, but suicide historically has been illegal and is
sometimes considered a common law crime, while medically assisted suicide is
strictly illegal in all but six states.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There's plenty to be said about
whether the government should regulate one's decisions that only affect
oneself in generality, but for the sake of this post we'll focus mostly on
those decisions regarding end of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;valuing-tomorrow&quot;&gt;Valuing Tomorrow&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I think it's necessary to establish why I value my future. I value my
own well-being, which encompasses pleasure and pain in both the present and the
future, and I value others' well-being, especially those I care for, like my
family. The former is primarily self-interested: I desire pleasure and I avoid
harm. The latter informs broader decisions I make: what I want out of my
studies, my future career, and so on. While I do derive fulfillment from
bettering the lives of those around me, and economists do lump all aspects of
decision-making under the notion of utility, for the sake of this discussion it
is useful to separate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does utility over time and intertemporal choice look like? We tend to
value consumption in the present more than consumption in the future. Given a
piece of candy that can be consumed today or five years from now, it's
reasonable to consume today. On the other hand, painful tasks like chores
tend to be pushed back to the future. Economists model this behavior using
discounting of future utility. The simplest model involves a parameter
\(\delta \in [0,1)\), where we make decisions that maximize
\[U := u_1 + \delta \mathop{\rm E}[u_2],\]
where \(u_1\) is utility derived from consumption in the first period (the
present) and \(\mathop{\rm E}[u_2]\) is the expected second period utility
(the future).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of \(u_1\) and \(u_2\) can then be separated into the two components
discussed earlier; we can write \(u_i(s_i,o_i)\) as an increasing function of
well-being \(s_i\) of oneself and \(o_i\) of others. Choices that either better
my personal life without impacting others or better others without impacting
myself are strictly good, for example. Those that better myself at the cost of
others or better others but demand sacrifice from me are more complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were to suddenly die painlessly in my sleep, there would be limited
loss to my personal well-being. I would go to bed the previous night
unsuspecting and happy as always, expecting the next day and the combination
of joy and hurt it brings, only I would not actually experience it. Given a
choice, however, I very much want to go to bed tonight waking up tomorrow. I
want to experience \(s_2\), since my current decision maximizes \(U\) which
is increasing in \(s_2\). I partly want to live the future for myself. But I
also care about \(o_2\). If I were to die, I think \(o_2\) takes an even
greater hit than \(s_2\). Death to me seems like a neutral thing, and I would
die not feeling any pain, but those that care about me would suffer loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determining what I value and why is a very hard question. I've written what I
consider to be a crude but fairly accurate model, at least at the time of
writing, but I fully expect that as my blog and I mature, my views on this
particular issue to change and develop more than most of my other beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;suicide&quot;&gt;Suicide&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legality of suicide is certainly a very difficult matter, and it's very
reasonable to default to laws that preserve life. But to what extent should
suicide really be regulated by the government?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I unequivocally believe that I have a personal responsibility to help people with
suicidal thoughts and encourage them to seek therapy. Someone who chooses
suicide implicitly finds life tomorrow not worth living, but I believe that
with proper help, they will find that life tomorrow has so much more
fulfillment than they had expected the day before. In this case, the skewed
perceived expectation of the future \(\mathop{\rm E}_*[u_2]\) is drastically
out of line with the actual expected value of future utility 
\(\mathop{\rm E}[u_2]\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this rationalization leads me to believe that I ought to do everything in
my power to save lives, I have a hard time deciding whether or not it is
grounds for the government to forcibly intervene. My inclination is that it is
generally not the government's role to determine whether or not an adult's
utility function is &quot;rational,&quot; or whether a future self would regret taking a
particular action. Nevertheless, it still makes perfect sense for the
government to limit the actions of children, so I'm not ready to make any
general statement here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;death-with-dignity&quot;&gt;Death with Dignity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, if someone were terminally ill and knew that for the rest of their
short life, they would be in excruciating pain, they ought to have the right to
escape pain gracefully. Perhaps the most well-known case of this today is that
of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brittany_Maynard&quot;&gt;Brittany Maynard&lt;/a&gt;, who
moved to Oregon to end her life in 2014 following a terminal brain cancer
diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is perfectly rational, in that 
\(\mathop{\rm E}_*[u_2] \approx \mathop{\rm E}[u_2]\) is actually a
reasonable representation of actual utility in the future. Using my simplified
value heuristic, prolonged pain harms personal well-being, and terminal illness
harms capability of improving others' well-being. The degree to which disease
impacts these values varies person by person, so while I think everyone in such
a position ought to have the right to death with dignity, I certainly don't
mean to imply that death by dignity is a path that people in this situation
should always take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A natural extension to consider is removing the stipulation of pain. If someone
had a terminal illness that didn't cause any bodily pain, but otherwise
incapacitated me, e.g. loss of memory or paralysis, then I think death with
dignity should still be granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;euthanasia-and-death-as-a-prior-arrangement&quot;&gt;Euthanasia and Death as a Prior Arrangement&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Euthanasia is slightly different from physician-assisted suicide. In assisted
suicide, a doctor prescribes lethal medication, and the agent self-administers
that medication when desired. In euthanasia, the agent might be unable to
self-administer; for example, they might be too weak to swallow the medication.
Euthanasia contrasts from physician-assisted suicide in that it is entirely
illegal in all the United States, despite the legality of physician-assisted
suicide in some states.  Euthanasia is only legal in a handful of countries in
the world, with the Netherlands and Belgium as notable examples.  Despite the
differences in legality, which I'll discuss in the next section, I don't find
anything morally different between these situations: one person wishes for
death, and another person complies, ensuring that death comes exactly as the
patient wishes it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What separates euthanasia from physician-assisted suicide is that an agent can
potentially enter a contract to be put down in the future, since the agent does
not need to be the one administering the medicine at the time of death. Playing
with timing makes euthanasia questionable. We allow people to opt into organ
donation programs, where in the event of brain death, their organs can be
harvested. It initially doesn't seem like an unreasonable leap to stipulate
that, in the future, should a disease or freak accident cause me to permanently
lose my memory and rational thought, though not quite leave brain dead, I give
up my body for organ donation. Perhaps this injury causes me to lash out
violently and mindlessly against everyone, including those I previously loved.
Or perhaps I know that my disease will result in the eventual loss of my
ability to think. It seems fair for the current me to agree to put this
potential future me down, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is quite troubling. What if in the future I don't want to die, even
though my present self willed it? Are the present and future selves the same
person? Indeed, in the present, it is precisely because I consider the future
me to be a different person whose values would not align with mine that I
agreed to have myself put down in the first place. This is surprisingly similar
to the intertemporal mindset of a saved suicidal person: in period 1, the agent
determines that living in period 2 is unfulfilling, but in period 2, the agent
then wants to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that in this example, the period 1 agent should not be allowed to
enter a contract that may result in the unwilling death of the period 2 self.
We certainly should not kill someone who is unwilling just because we think it
is for the better: this seems pretty clear to me to be murder. Should the
period 1 self not wish to grant the period 2 agent control of their body, then
they must take proactive action in period 1 rather than enter a contract to
have themselves killed in the future.  Consequently, to be eligible for
euthanasia, I believe that an agent must desire it at the time of
administration, not at some previous time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;contrasting-with-current-laws&quot;&gt;Contrasting with Current Laws&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I find not trying to prevent medically assisted suicide more
moral than not trying to prevent a normal suicide, though current laws indicate
that the government believes the opposite, as physician-assisted suicide is
more explicit in its illegality in more states. Note also that in almost all
circumstances, we allow people to refuse life-saving medical treatment.
Choosing to die painlessly seems strictly better than dying painfully without
any medication at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I find euthanasia only proper when the patient desires death at the
moment it is administered, I find euthanasia more justifiably illegal, as the
cases where euthanasia is most applicable are also those where the patient is
most vulnerable and incapacitated. Our legal system hinges on responsibility:
granting doctors the right to terminate their patients, even with the consent
of the patient, opens up room for abuse. If, for example, only verbal consent
at the time of administration were required for euthanasia to be justified,
then even with witnesses, determining whether a doctor conducted themself
within the law is difficult. If we require written consent, then presumably the
patient is capable of administering the medicine themself anyway, so only
physician-assisted suicide is necessary. Morally, I think that there's no
difference between written, verbal, or any other means of consent, but I
understand that legally it may be necessary to distinguish them. The intent of
the patient is much more clear in assisted suicide than in euthanasia, and our
laws must err on the side of patient protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I think it's worth contrasting legislation meant strictly to protect your future self from your current self from most legislation, whose primary purpose is to restrict your actions to benefit other people. Seat belt laws are meant mostly to restrain you to keep you safe, as wearing a seat belt has minimal positive externalities of the safety of other drivers. Social Security is less clear, since it can be seen as a redistribution of income from the young to the old, but over a lifetime it largely does not redistribute income from the rich to the poor, so I think it's better to classify Social Security as a compulsory retirement plan rather than income redistribution. On the other hand, while Obamacare forces us to buy health insurance, the primary purpose of this is not to babysit us. The individual mandate's main purpose is to spread the cost of healthcare across the entire country to make the other key provision, banning price discrimination based on pre-existing conditions, feasible. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, the five states with legislation allowing death with dignity are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deathwithdignity.org/learn/death-with-dignity-acts/&quot;&gt;Oregon since 1998, Vermont since 2013, Washington since 2009, and California and Colorado since 2016&lt;/a&gt;. Montana allows for death with dignity via a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baxter_v._Montana&quot;&gt;court ruling in 2009&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">To what extent should people be able to control their futures, and to what extent can the government take that away? Last week, Jacob and I were discussing whether the government has done too little or too much in shaping our life decisions. The United States gives its citizens plenty of agency in weighing the short and long term. I can choose what food I eat and how much I exercise, as it's entirely my decision whether having a satisfying but unhealthy lifestyle is worth shaving years off the end of my life. I assess risk constantly, from inching closer to the edge of a cliff for that perfect photo to simply biking to and from work, internalizing the probability that I get into an accident. I can choose my career: some jobs are more financially risky while some are physically more dangerous, some better fit my skill set while others I find more intrinsically appealling, but the government leaves all of these factors up to the market to set prices and wages, and from there I make my own choice.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Egorychev, Part 2</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/15/egorychev-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Egorychev, Part 2" /><published>2017-07-16T08:30:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-07-16T08:30:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/15/egorychev-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/15/egorychev-2/">&lt;p&gt;Ross sent me an interesting math problem last month, and I detailed my attempt
at a solution in a &lt;a href=&quot;/jekyll/posts/2017/07/06/egorychev/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; a little
more than a week ago. With his substantial help, I was finally able to make
some headway, and the following solution is much more a recreation of his
rather than my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let \(0 \le a &amp;lt; 1\) and \(n \in \mathbb{Z}^+\), and define
\[ I_n = \left( 1-a^2 \right)^{n-1/2} \int_0^{2\pi} \frac{d\theta}{\left( 1 + a\cos\theta \right)^n}. \]
Express \(I_n\) as a polynomial in \(a\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my earlier post, the reader should mind two key insights
using complex analysis: the first, a treatment of \(\cos\theta\) I'd dealt
with regularly, and the second, the Egorychev method, which I hadn't yet
encountered. The beginning of the solution is much the same, so one who has
already read my previous post on this problem can comfortably skip through the
first steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first get rid of the integral as quickly as possible and worry about
simplifying later, applying a standard substitution of \(z = e^{i\theta}\),
transforming the real integral into a complex one. We then have 
\(\cos\theta = \frac{1}{2} \left( z + \frac{1}{z} \right)\) and 
\(dz = iz \,d\theta\), and the integral becomes
\[ \int_0^{2\pi} \frac{d\theta}{\left( 1 + a\cos\theta \right)^n} = \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{1}{iz} \frac{dz}{\left( 1 + \frac{a}{2} \left( z + \frac{1}{z} \right) \right)^n}. \]
If \(a = 0\), \(I_n = 2\pi\) immediately; otherwise, we have
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{1}{iz} \frac{dz}{\left( 1 + \frac{a}{2} \left( z + \frac{1}{z} \right) \right)^n} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{i} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{z^{n-1} \,dz}{\left( \frac{a}{2} z^2 + z + \frac{a}{2} \right)^n} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{i} \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{z^{n-1} \,dz}{\left( \left( z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right) \left( z - \frac{-1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right) \right)^n} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dz^{n-1}} \left( \frac{z^{n-1}}{\left( z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^n } \right) \right\rvert_{z = \frac{-1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}},
\end{align}
by Cauchy's integral formula. For the sake of simplifying notation, we
substitute \(w = z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}\), giving us
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dz^{n-1}} \left( \frac{z^{n-1}}{\left( z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^n } \right) \right\rvert_{z = \frac{-1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dw^{n-1}} \left( \frac{\left(w + \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^{n-1}}{ w^n } \right) \right\rvert_{w = \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dw^{n-1}} \left( \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^k w^{-k-1} \right) \right\rvert_{w = \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k} \frac{(-1)^{n-1} (n-1+k)!}{k!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^k w^{-k-n} \right\rvert_{w = \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^k \left( \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^{-k-n} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{2} \right)^k \left( \sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{-k-n}.
\end{align}
We then have
\begin{align}
I_n &amp;amp;= \left( \sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{2n-1} 2\pi (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{2} \right)^k \left( \sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{-k-n} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( -\frac{1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{2} \right)^k \left( \sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{n-1-k}.
\end{align}
Again, for the sake of simplifying notation, let \(x = \sqrt{1-a^2}\). Notice
that there very well may be terms of odd powers of \(x\), so we have no
indication yet that the resulting value will end up being a polynomial in
\(a\). We then have
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } 2\pi (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1 + k)!}{k!k!(n-1 - k)!} \left( -\frac{1 + x}{2} \right)^k x^{n-1 - k} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \sum_{j=0}^k \frac{(n-1 + k)!}{k! (n-1 - k)! j! (k - j)!} (-2)^{-k} x^{n-1 - j}.
\end{align}
This is a minor change from my previous solution. We expand 
\( \left( \frac{1 + x}{2} \right)^k = \sum_{j=0}^k \binom{k}{j} \left(\frac{x}{2}\right)^{k-j} \) 
rather than using \(j\) as the exponent; this avoids some annoying
reindexing, as the resulting exponent of \(x\) in the double sum depends only
on \(j\) rather than a combination. Swapping the sums gives
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } 2\pi \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \sum_{j=0}^k \frac{(n-1 + k)!}{k! (n-1 - k)! j! (k - j)!} (-2)^{-k} x^{n-1 - j} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \sum_{j=0}^{n-1} x^{n-1 - j} \sum_{k=j}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1 + k)!}{k! (n-1 - k)! j! (k - j)!} (-2)^{-k} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \sum_{j=0}^{n-1} x^{n-1 - j} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1 + k}{k - j} \binom{n-1 + j}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k} (-2)^{-k} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \sum_{j=0}^{n-1} x^{n-1 - j} \binom{n-1 + j}{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1 + k}{k - j} \binom{n-1}{k} (-2)^{-k},
\end{align}
where we extend the sum over \(k\) to start at \(0\), as terms where 
\(k &amp;lt; j\) are \(0\) anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we apply the Egorychev method. Up until this point I'd been in a mad dash
to get rid of the integral as quickly as possible, and then simplify as much as
possible, but then I was blocked by a binomial sum I couldn't handle. The
Egorychev method involves introducing complex contour integrals to simplify
binomial identities, which seems a little backwards – after all, didn't we
just work so hard to get rid of a contour integral in the first place? Well,
let's see what this method really does.
Our main tool is the following identity:
\[
\binom{s}{t} = \frac{1}{2\pi i} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(1+z)^s \,dz}{z^{t+1}}
\]
There are other possible integrals we could use to express binomials, but this
will suffice for this problem. My main intuition here for why we would ever
want to substitute this is that binomials are nice in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each individual binomial is pretty arithmetically: 
\(\binom{s}{t} = \frac{s!}{t!(s-t)!}\).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Binomials combine to be pretty algebraically: 
\(\sum_{t=0}^s \binom{s}{t}z^t = (1+z)^s\) is the simplest example, and we
can think of generating functions more generally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are nice ways combinatorially to think about binomials using both these
facts simultaneously, but here we're stuck with individual binomials in a sum
that doesn't allow them to play nicely off of each other, especially because of
this nasty \( (-2)^{n-1 - k} \) term. We'd like to be able to take advantage
of property 2, which is what the Egorychev method affords us. Applying the
method to the binomial \(\binom{n-1 + k}{k - j}\) gives us
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1 + k}{k - j} \binom{n-1}{k} (-2)^{-k} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi i} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(1+z)^{n-1 + k} \,dz}{z^{k - j + 1}} \binom{n-1}{k} (-2)^{-k} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi i} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(1+z)^{n-1}}{z^{-j + 1}} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k} \left( -\frac{1}{2z} - \frac{1}{2} \right)^k \,dz \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi i} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(1+z)^{n-1}}{z^{n-1 - j + 1}} \left( -\frac{1}{2z} + \frac{1}{2} \right)^{n-1} \,dz \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2^{n-1}} \frac{1}{2\pi i} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{\left( 1 - z^2 \right)^{n-1} \,dz}{z^{n-1 - j + 1}} \\
&amp;amp;= \begin{cases} 0 &amp;amp; 2 \not\mid n-1 - j \\ \frac{1}{2^{n-1}} \binom{n-1}{(n-1 - j)/2} (-1)^{(n-1 - j)/2} &amp;amp; 2 \mid n-1 - j. \end{cases}
\end{align}
Now let \(k' = \frac{n-1 - j}{2}\). We can then write
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } 2\pi \sum_{j=0}^{n-1} x^{n-1 - j} \binom{n-1 + j}{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1 + k}{k - j} \binom{n-1}{k} (-2)^{-k} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{k'=0}^{n-1} x^{2k'} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k'} (-1)^{k'} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{k'=0}^{n-1} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k'} (-1)^{k'} \left( 1 - a^2 \right)^{k'},
\end{align}
which is indeed a polynomial in \(a\). Expanding once more and swapping the
sums, we have
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{k'=0}^{n-1} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k'} (-1)^{k'} \left( 1 - a^2 \right)^{k'} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{k'=0}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k'} (-1)^{k'} \sum_{m=0}^{k'} \binom{k'}{m} (-1)^m a^{2m} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{m=0}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} (-1)^m a^{2m} \sum_{k'=m}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k'} \binom{k'}{m} (-1)^{k'} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{m=0}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} (-1)^m a^{2m} \sum_{k'=m}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{m} \binom{n-1 - m}{k' - m} (-1)^{k'} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{m=0}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} (-1)^m a^{2m} \binom{n-1}{m} \sum_{k'=m}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1 - m}{k' - m} (-1)^{k'}.
\end{align}
We now use the Egorychev method again to the binomial 
\(\binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1}\):
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } \sum_{k'=m}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1 - m}{k' - m} (-1)^{k'} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2 \pi i} \sum_{k'=m}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(1+z)^{2(n-1) - 2k'} \,dz}{z^n} \binom{n-1 - m}{k' - m} (-1)^{k'} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2 \pi i} (-1)^m \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{1}{z^n} \sum_{k'=m}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \binom{n-1 - m}{k' - m} \left( 1 + 2z + z^2 \right)^{n-1 - k'} (-1)^{k' - m} \,dz \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2 \pi i} (-1)^m \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{1}{z^n} \left( 2z + z^2 \right)^{n-1 - m} \,dz \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2 \pi i} (-1)^m \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(2 + z)^{n-1 - m} \,dz}{z^{m + 1}} \\
&amp;amp;= (-1)^m 2^{n-1 - 2m} \binom{n-1 - m}{m}.
\end{align}
Finishing, we have
\begin{align}
I_n &amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{m=0}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} (-1)^m a^{2m} \binom{n-1}{m} \sum_{k'=m}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} \binom{2(n-1) - 2k'}{n-1} \binom{n-1 - m}{k' - m} (-1)^{k'} \\
I_n &amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{m=0}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor} (-1)^m a^{2m} \binom{n-1}{m} (-1)^m 2^{n-1 - 2m} \binom{n-1 - m}{m} \\
I_n &amp;amp;= 2\pi \sum_{m=0}^{\lfloor (n-1)/2 \rfloor}\binom{n-1}{m} \binom{n-1 - m}{m} \left(\frac{a}{2}\right)^{2m}.
\end{align}
This end result is very nice. The general strategy in this problem centered
around simplifying sums of the form 
\(\sum_{k=0}^{n} \binom{s}{t} \binom{n}{k} c^k\), where the first binomial
was manipulated using Egorychev, and the resulting exponential combines with
the second binomial to simplify the sum.  The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egorychev_method&quot;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; on
the Egorychev method highlights some examples of more complicated uses of the
method, using more than just one integral at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Ross noted to me that this integral actually has applications in
physics: &quot;this integral actually comes out of computing the time averages
\(\left\langle r^n \right\rangle\) of a Kepler orbit 
\(r = r_0/(1+a\cos(\theta))\).&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ross sent me an interesting math problem last month, and I detailed my attempt at a solution in a blog post a little more than a week ago. With his substantial help, I was finally able to make some headway, and the following solution is much more a recreation of his rather than my own.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prius</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/11/prius/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prius" /><published>2017-07-12T08:30:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-07-12T08:30:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/11/prius</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/11/prius/">&lt;p&gt;I landed in Seattle for the first time, and I have never seen so many
Priuses&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in one place as in the Lyft pickup line. Apparently drivers using
ride-sharing apps, in order to use the pickup queue at the airport, need to
drive cars with at least 40 MPG. Go figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Apparently the public voted the plural of &quot;Prius&quot; to be &quot;Prii,&quot; which Toyota then made official, but I think the term is silly. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I landed in Seattle for the first time, and I have never seen so many Priuses1 in one place as in the Lyft pickup line. Apparently drivers using ride-sharing apps, in order to use the pickup queue at the airport, need to drive cars with at least 40 MPG. Go figure. Apparently the public voted the plural of &quot;Prius&quot; to be &quot;Prii,&quot; which Toyota then made official, but I think the term is silly. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Egorychev</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/06/egorychev/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Egorychev" /><published>2017-07-07T06:30:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-07-07T06:30:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/06/egorychev</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/07/06/egorychev/">&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks ago my friend Ross sent me an interesting integral involving a
neat trick called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egorychev_method&quot;&gt;Egorychev method&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let \(0 \le a &amp;lt; 1\) and \(n \in \mathbb{Z}^+\), and define
\[ I_n = \left( 1-a^2 \right)^{n-1/2} \int_0^{2\pi} \frac{d\theta}{\left( 1 + a\cos\theta \right)^n}. \]
Express \(I_n\) as a polynomial in \(a\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven't completely simplified the end polynomial (note: a full solution can
be found in a &lt;a href=&quot;/jekyll/posts/2017/07/15/egorychev-2/&quot;&gt;newer blog post&lt;/a&gt;), but
the key insights using complex analysis – the first, a treatment of
\(\cos\theta\) I'd dealt with regularly, and the second, the Egorychev
method, which I hadn't yet encountered – are present and worth sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intuition was to get rid of the integral as quickly as possible and worry
about simplifying later. I therefore immediately applied a standard
substitution of \(z = e^{i\theta}\), transforming the real integral into a
complex one. We then have 
\(\cos\theta = \frac{1}{2} \left( z + \frac{1}{z} \right)\) 
and \(dz = iz \,d\theta\), and the integral becomes
\[ \int_0^{2\pi} \frac{d\theta}{\left( 1 + a\cos\theta \right)^n} = \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{1}{iz} \frac{dz}{\left( 1 + \frac{a}{2} \left( z + \frac{1}{z} \right) \right)^n}. \]
If \(a = 0\), \(I_n = 2\pi\) immediately; otherwise, we have
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{1}{iz} \frac{dz}{\left( 1 + \frac{a}{2} \left( z + \frac{1}{z} \right) \right)^n} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{i} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{z^{n-1} \,dz}{\left( \frac{a}{2} z^2 + z + \frac{a}{2} \right)^n} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{i} \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \oint_{\lvert z \rvert=1} \frac{z^{n-1} \,dz}{\left( \left( z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right) \left( z - \frac{-1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right) \right)^n} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dz^{n-1}} \left( \frac{z^{n-1}}{\left( z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^n } \right) \right\rvert_{z = \frac{-1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}},
\end{align}
by Cauchy's integral formula. For the sake of simplifying notation, we
substitute \(w = z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}\), giving us
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dz^{n-1}} \left( \frac{z^{n-1}}{\left( z - \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^n } \right) \right\rvert_{z = \frac{-1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dw^{n-1}} \left( \frac{\left(w + \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^{n-1}}{ w^n } \right) \right\rvert_{w = \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \frac{d^{n-1}}{dw^{n-1}} \left( \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^k w^{-k-1} \right) \right\rvert_{w = \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n \frac{1}{(n-1)!} \left. \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \binom{n-1}{k} \frac{(-1)^{n-1} (n-1+k)!}{k!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^k w^{-k-n} \right\rvert_{w = \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a}} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \left( \frac{2}{a} \right)^n (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^k \left( \frac{2\sqrt{1-a^2}}{a} \right)^{-k-n} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{2} \right)^k \left( \sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{-k-n}.
\end{align}
We then have
\begin{align}
I_n &amp;amp;= \left( \sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{2n-1} 2\pi (-1)^{n-1} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( \frac{-1 - \sqrt{1-a^2}}{2} \right)^k \left( \sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{-k-n} \\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1+k)!}{k!k!(n-1-k)!} \left( \frac{1 + \sqrt{1-a^2}}{2} \right)^k \left( -\sqrt{1-a^2} \right)^{n-1-k}.
\end{align}
Again, for the sake of simplifying notation, let \(x = \sqrt{1-a^2}\). Notice
that there very well may be terms of odd powers of \(x\), so we have no
indication yet that the resulting value will end up being a polynomial in
\(a\). We then have
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } 2\pi \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{(n-1 + k)!}{k!k!(n-1 - k)!} \left( \frac{1 + x}{2} \right)^k (-x)^{n-1 - k} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \sum_{j=0}^k \frac{(n-1 + k)!}{k! (n-1 - k)! j! (k - j)!} (-2)^{n-1 - k} x^{n-1 - k + j}.
\end{align}
Rearranging with \(k' = n-1 - k\) and  \(j' = k' + j = n-1 - k + j\), and
then swapping the sums, we have
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \sum_{j=0}^k \frac{(n-1 + k)!}{k! (n-1 - k)! j! (k - j)!} (-2)^{n-1 - k} x^{n-1 - k + j} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{k'=0}^{n-1} \sum_{j'=k'}^{n-1} \frac{(2(n-1) - k')!}{(n-1 - k')! k'! (j' - k')! (n-1 - j')!} (-2)^{k'} x^{j'} \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{j=0}^{n-1} x^j \sum_{k=0}^j \binom{2(n-1)-k}{n-1} \binom{n-1}{j} \binom{j}{k} (-2)^k,
\end{align}
where in the last step \(k\) and \(j\) are written in place of \(k'\) and
\(j'\) for convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we apply the Egorychev method. Up until this point I'd been in a mad dash
to get rid of the integral as quickly as possible, and then simplify as much as
possible, but then I was blocked by a binomial sum I couldn't handle. The
Egorychev method involves introducing complex contour integrals to simplify
binomial identities, which seems a little backwards – after all, didn't we
just work so hard to get rid of a contour integral in the first place? Well,
let's see what this method really does.  Our main tool is the following
identity:
\[
\binom{s}{t} = \frac{1}{2\pi i} \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(1+z)^s \,dz}{z^{t+1}}
\]
There are other possible integrals we could use to express binomials, but this
will suffice for this problem. My main intuition here for why we would ever
want to substitute this is that binomials are nice in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each individual binomial is pretty arithmetically: 
\(\binom{s}{t} = \frac{s!}{t!(s-t)!}\).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Binomials combine to be pretty algebraically: 
\(\sum_{t=0}^s \binom{s}{t}z^t = (1+z)^s\) is the simplest example, and we
can think of generating functions more generally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are nice ways combinatorially to think about binomials using both these
facts simultaneously, but here we're stuck with individual binomials in a sum
that doesn't allow them to play nicely off of each other, especially because of
this nasty \( (-2)^k \) term. We'd like to be able to take advantage of
property 2, which is what the Egorychev method affords us. Applying the method
to the binomial \(\binom{2(n-1)-k}{n-1}\) gives us
\begin{align}
&amp;amp;\phantom{ {}={} } \sum_{k=0}^j \binom{2(n-1)-k}{n-1} \binom{j}{k} (-2)^k \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi i}  \sum_{k=0}^j \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{(1+z)^{2(n-1)-k} \,dz}{z^n} \binom{j}{k} (-2)^k \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi i}  \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{1}{z^n} (1+z)^{2(n-1)-j} \sum_{k=0}^j \binom{j}{k} (1+z)^{j-k} (-2)^k \,dz \\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi i}  \oint_{\lvert z \rvert = \varepsilon} \frac{1}{z^n} (z+1)^{2(n-1)-j} (z-1)^j \,dz \\
&amp;amp;= \sum_{k=0}^j \binom{2(n-1)-j}{n-1 - k} \binom{j}{k} (-1)^k,
\end{align}
giving us the identity
\[
\sum_{k=0}^j \binom{2(n-1)-k}{n-1} \binom{j}{k} (-2)^k = \sum_{k=0}^j \binom{2(n-1)-j}{n-1 - k} \binom{j}{k} (-1)^k.
\]
This is considerably nicer. In particular, look what happens when \(j\) is
odd! By pairing the terms up by \(k\) and \(j-k\), we have
\[
\binom{2(n-1)-j}{n-1 - k} \binom{j}{k} (-1)^k + \binom{2(n-1)-j}{(n-1) - (j-k)} \binom{j}{j-k} (-1)^{j-k} = 0,
\]
so therefore
\[
\binom{n-1}{j} \sum_{k=0}^j \binom{2(n-1)-j}{n-1 - k} \binom{j}{k} (-1)^k
\]
is \(0\) for odd \(j\)! Then we have
\[
I_n = \frac{2\pi}{2^{n-1}} \sum_{\substack{j \in [0, n-1], \\ 2 \mid j }} \left( 1-a^2 \right)^{j/2} \binom{n-1}{j} \sum_{k=0}^j \binom{2(n-1)-j}{n-1 - k} \binom{j}{k} (-1)^k,
\]
which is indeed a polynomial in \(a\), as desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that someone more clever than I could manage to get from the first
contour integral to the last without evaluating the former and reintroducing
the latter or establish the binomial sum identity using purely elementary
means, since as much of a nuisance exponentials are, \(2\) is still a very
nice number. Whether or not the Egorychev method is necessary for this problem
specifically, I felt that this problem served as a neat introduction to its
concept and set me up to explore more substantive applications of the Egorychev
method in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A couple weeks ago my friend Ross sent me an interesting integral involving a neat trick called the Egorychev method.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A N G E R Y</title><link href="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/06/28/angery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A N G E R Y" /><published>2017-06-29T07:50:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-06-29T07:50:00+04:00</updated><id>alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/06/28/angery</id><content type="html" xml:base="alwayswimmin.github.io/jekyll/posts/2017/06/28/angery/">&lt;p&gt;angery &amp;gt;:(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;textarea id=&quot;angery-input&quot; rows=&quot;4&quot; cols=&quot;50&quot; placeholder=&quot;angery reaccs only&quot; autofocus=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/textarea&gt;

&lt;textarea readonly=&quot;&quot; id=&quot;angery-output&quot; rows=&quot;4&quot; cols=&quot;50&quot;&gt;
&lt;/textarea&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;continuous&quot; name=&quot;continuous&quot; value=&quot;continuous&quot; checked=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;label for=&quot;continuous&quot;&gt;continuous conversion&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;capitalize&quot; name=&quot;capitalize&quot; value=&quot;capitalize&quot; checked=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;label for=&quot;capitalize&quot;&gt;capitalize&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;extra-space&quot; name=&quot;extra-space&quot; value=&quot;extra-space&quot; /&gt;
&lt;label for=&quot;extra-space&quot;&gt;extra spaces between words&lt;/label&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;button&quot; id=&quot;convert&quot; name=&quot;convert&quot; value=&quot;convert&quot; onclick=&quot;convert()&quot; style=&quot;visibility: hidden&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
var input_area = document.getElementById(&quot;angery-input&quot;);
var output_area = document.getElementById(&quot;angery-output&quot;);
var convert_button = document.getElementById(&quot;convert&quot;);

var continuous_checkbox = document.getElementById(&quot;continuous&quot;);

var continuous = continuous_checkbox.checked;
function continuous_checkbox_change(event) {
  continuous = this.checked;
  if(continuous) {
    convert_button.style.visibility = &quot;hidden&quot;;
    convert();
  } else {
    convert_button.style.visibility = &quot;visible&quot;;
  }
}
continuous_checkbox.addEventListener('change', continuous_checkbox_change);

var capitalize_checkbox = document.getElementById(&quot;capitalize&quot;);
var extra_space_checkbox = document.getElementById(&quot;extra-space&quot;);

var capitalize = capitalize_checkbox.checked;
var extra_space = extra_space_checkbox.checked;

capitalize_checkbox.addEventListener('change', convert);
extra_space_checkbox.addEventListener('change', convert);

// https://stackoverflow.com/a/14029861
if (input_area.addEventListener) {
  input_area.addEventListener('input', function() {
    // event handling code for sane browsers
    continuous = continuous_checkbox.checked;
    if(continuous) {
      convert();
    }
  }, false);
} else if (input_area.attachEvent) {
  input_area.attachEvent('onpropertychange', function() {
    // IE-specific event handling code
    continuous = continuous_checkbox.checked;
    if(continuous) {
      convert();
    }
  });
}

function convert() {
    var input = input_area.value;
    capitalize = capitalize_checkbox.checked;
    extra_space = extra_space_checkbox.checked;
    if(capitalize) {
      input = input.toUpperCase();
    }
    var input_arr = input.split(&quot;&quot;);
    var output_arr = new Array();
    var first_in_word = true;
    for(var i = 0; i &lt; input_arr.length; i++) {
    	if(/\s/.test(input_arr[i])) {
            // is whitespace
            output_arr.push(input_arr[i]);
            if(extra_space &amp;&amp; input_arr[i] == ' ') {
              output_arr.push(' ');
            }
            first_in_word = true;
            continue;
        }
        if(!first_in_word) {
            output_arr.push(&quot; &quot;);
        }
        output_arr.push(input_arr[i]);
        first_in_word = false;
    }
    var output = output_arr.join(&quot;&quot;);
    output_area.value = output;
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">angery &amp;gt;:(</summary></entry></feed>